<collection><etd_ms:thesis xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/ http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/etdms.xsd" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:etd_ms="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/">
        <etd_ms:title>Artificial Intelligence for Spectrum-Aware Autonomous Wireless Networks</etd_ms:title>
        <etd_ms:creator>AbdelKhalek, Nada</etd_ms:creator>
        <etd_ms:subject/>
        <etd_ms:description>Spectrum is one of the most vital public resources, carrying wireless communications for mobile phones, satellites, and emergency services. Traditionally, spectrum has been exclusively licensed, resulting in occasional underutilization. However, with the rapid proliferation of wireless devices, spectrum congestion has become inevitable, especially in unlicensed networks such as the Internet of Things (IoT), vehicular, and Unmanned Aerial Vehicles (UAVs), where devices rely on a limited number of public frequency bands that may not support large-scale communications. This contradiction between licensed spectrum underutilization and unlicensed spectrum congestion necessitates a rethinking of spectrum allocation and management strategies. In this thesis, we draw inspiration from Cognitive Radio (CR) technology, which equips radio devices with capabilities such as perception, reasoning, and judgment, and extend it to “intelligent radio” that integrates both cognition and learning capabilities. Our work advocates a shift from traditional model-driven approaches that rely on domain knowledge and strong assumptions to data-driven methods that learn directly from raw data and constant interactions with the environment. With the support of Artificial Intelligence (AI), we design intelligent spectrum borrowing and spectrum-sharing techniques that enable wireless devices to operate opportunistically on licensed bands. Specifically, this thesis explores how AI can endow wireless devices with context-awareness, self-optimization, and self-management capabilities for tasks such as dynamic spectrum access, power management, resource allocation, and ensuring security. Additionally, we develop solutions and frameworks for self-sustaining wireless devices that leverage Energy Harvesting (EH), bringing us closer to the realization of green networks. Our AI-driven algorithms are designed with computational efficiency in mind to minimize the burden on resource-constrained devices.

To drive context-aware intelligence in large-scale cooperative networks, we develop various unsupervised Machine Learning (ML) approaches for spectrum sensing. Unlike existing methods, the proposed frameworks operate without the need for labeled data, prior knowledge of the radio environment, or cooperation between licensed and unlicensed users. The approach ensures robust spectrum sensing while minimizing computational overhead for unlicensed users with limited capabilities. Moreover, we investigate how dimensionality reduction can improve computational efficiency and model generalizability. We expand the use of unsupervised learning to hybrid CR networks to allow devices to detect all licensed network states, opening up new opportunities for dynamic spectrum access.

To improve spectrum reasoning and analysis, we introduce some of the first fully unsupervised, data-efficient deep representation learning frameworks. These frameworks are designed to learn effective and disentangled representations of radio environment data. We demonstrate their effectiveness in significantly enhancing spectrum gap detection in small-scale cooperative networks. Additionally, we tackle key challenges of unsupervised learning, such as sensitivity to initialization and the need for predefined cluster counts. In large-scale networks, we propose a generative deep representation model that not only learns efficient representations but also captures the distribution of radio environment data, enabling the generation of new, unseen samples.

To facilitate edge intelligence and enhance the privacy of intelligent radios, we propose the first fully unsupervised deep Federated Learning (FL) framework for secure and distributed spectrum sensing in large-scale mobile networks. By leveraging user mobility across a large geographical area, the method enhances spatio-temporal diversity without requiring the transmission of private data to a central unit for processing. Instead, data is collected locally, and a shared model is collaboratively trained in a decentralized manner, significantly reducing communication overhead and safeguarding user privacy. 

We tackle the growing challenge of spectrum scarcity in Cognitive IoT (CIoT) networks, where the demand for spectrum is increasing due to the expansion of connected devices. To address this, we develop intelligent and adaptive control algorithms for the joint management of network resources in spectrum-sharing environments. First, we formulate optimization problems under various constraints and model the decision-making process of a CIoT agent in the dynamic radio environment. We then propose two novel Deep Reinforcement Learning (DRL) algorithms that enable devices to autonomously learn operational strategies to optimize network resources and maximize long-term throughput without comprehensive prior knowledge. Additionally, we introduce innovative exploration strategies to enhance the CIoT agent's ability to identify optimal actions that maximize data rates. Considering the resource limitations of these networks, the algorithms are designed to be lightweight to reduce computational burdens on users. We also integrate EH techniques, such as Wireless Power Transfer (WPT) and Simultaneous Wireless Information and Power Transfer (SWIPT), to make these networks self-sustaining.

Finally, to develop dynamic strategies for navigating hostile spectrum-sharing environments impacted by jamming attacks, we propose an intelligent DRL approach that does not rely on frequency hopping. This algorithm is designed for rapid convergence, energy efficiency, and adaptability to adversarial conditions. We begin by formulating the optimization problem of power control under various constraints and modeling the decision-making process of the CIoT agent in such a hostile environment. Then, we introduce a novel interference-aware exploration strategy that enables the CIoT device to autonomously learn a transmission strategy, effectively mitigating jamming attacks and maximizing performance. Furthermore, we leverage WPT EH to allow the CIoT agent to convert jamming interference into a valuable resource for recharging.

In summary, the contributions of this thesis lay the foundation for a new generation of intelligent, autonomous wireless networks that are both spectrum-aware and agile, capable of optimizing resources and adapting to dynamic and complex environments.</etd_ms:description>
        <etd_ms:publisher>Concordia University</etd_ms:publisher>
        <etd_ms:contributor role="advisor">Hamouda, Walaa</etd_ms:contributor>
        <etd_ms:date>2025-03-10</etd_ms:date>
        <etd_ms:type>Electronic Thesis or Dissertation</etd_ms:type>
        <etd_ms:identifier>TC-QMG-995477</etd_ms:identifier>
        <etd_ms:format>text</etd_ms:format>
        <etd_ms:identifier>https://spectrum.library.concordia.ca/id/eprint/995477/1/Abdelkhalek_PhD_S2025.pdf</etd_ms:identifier>
        <etd_ms:language>en</etd_ms:language><etd_ms:degree>
        <etd_ms:name>Ph. D.</etd_ms:name>
        <etd_ms:level>phd</etd_ms:level>
        <etd_ms:discipline>Electrical and Computer Engineering</etd_ms:discipline>
        <etd_ms:grantor>Concordia University</etd_ms:grantor></etd_ms:degree></etd_ms:thesis><etd_ms:thesis xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/ http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/etdms.xsd" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:etd_ms="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/">
        <etd_ms:title>Grid and Inverter-Fed Induction Machine Emulation</etd_ms:title>
        <etd_ms:creator>Afrasiabi, Seyedeh Nazanin</etd_ms:creator>
        <etd_ms:subject/>
        <etd_ms:description>Power-hardware-in-the-loop (PHIL) based machine emulation is increasingly being used as an effective approach for simplifying the testing of electric drive systems. The PHIL-based machine emulator systems control the power converters or power amplifiers in order to mimic machine behavior. Control of the machine emulator is achieved with the help of a machine model running on a real-time controller. Utilizing a motor emulator allows performance testing of the physical machine and its controller before the manufacturing process, reducing risks and costs. This methodology enables testing of different drive inverter faults, including diode rectifier faults, transistor switch faults, and line-to-line faults, without risking damage to the machine. Moreover, it can be applied to test various faulty machines and grid faults, such as open circuits, short circuits, and unbalanced faults. Therefore, this approach finds extensive application in diverse industrial sectors, including military, aerospace, and electric vehicles.
Various open research challenges exist in this domain, all of which aim to improve the accuracy and utility of this test methodology. Emulation accuracy depends on various factors, namely the detailed mathematical model of the electrical machine, the design and selection of the control for the emulation system, and the selection of emulator hardware technologies. Since PHIL-based machine emulation is a relatively novel testing methodology, there is a need to develop a high-performance, highly accurate test bench. Therefore, this PhD work aims to develop an accurate motor emulation test bench to truly validate the performance of the motor, drive inverter, and drive inverter control prior to manufacturing the prototype motor.
A reliable and flexible grid is crucial for PHIL-based machine emulation system test benches. To achieve this, grid emulators are introduced to enhance the reliability and flexibility of motor emulation systems. Currently, power amplifiers are popular choices for emulators due to their high bandwidth, compact size, and ease of control. However, amplifiers are designed for specific voltage ratings, and when higher voltage is required, a step-up transformer is added to the amplifier output. The connection of the transformer at the output of the amplifier can impact the performance and characteristics of the grid emulator system. Therefore, this research work aims to characterize the grid emulator system with an amplifier and transformer under various operating conditions.
Machine emulation accuracy depends on various factors, with one of the key factors being the selection of emulator hardware technology. Thus, this research compares three types of machine emulation systems: one utilizing a conventional IGBT-based hard switching power converter, another employing a high-bandwidth soft switching power converter, and the third using a linear amplifier. Detailed configurations and control descriptions for these systems are provided in this work. Comparative experimental studies are conducted, and the obtained results are then compared with those of the physical induction motor (IM) to verify the emulation performance.
The typical voltage source inverter is employed as an emulator converter in motor emulation systems. However, this converter introduces various harmonics into the motor emulation system, primarily attributed to dead time, switching components, and control signals. These harmonics can deteriorate motor emulation accuracy. Therefore, it is important to investigate and compensate for emulator converter harmonics in the motor emulation system. Hence, this PhD work will also explore this topic.
The induction motor drive with an LC filter configuration enables smooth pulse width modulation (PWM) output voltages of the motor drives. Moreover, employing high-performance, high-bandwidth class D power amplifiers as emulator converters enhances the system's bandwidth, thereby ensuring accurate machine emulation. Another open research topic that could improve motor emulation systems is testing electric drives with filters. Testing such a machine drive using conventional emulator structures would be challenging. Therefore, this PhD work will also investigate this topic.</etd_ms:description>
        <etd_ms:publisher>Concordia University</etd_ms:publisher>
        <etd_ms:contributor role="advisor">Lai, Chunyan</etd_ms:contributor>
        <etd_ms:contributor role="advisor">Pillay, Pragasen</etd_ms:contributor>
        <etd_ms:date>2025-05-01</etd_ms:date>
        <etd_ms:type>Electronic Thesis or Dissertation</etd_ms:type>
        <etd_ms:identifier>TC-QMG-995478</etd_ms:identifier>
        <etd_ms:format>text</etd_ms:format>
        <etd_ms:identifier>https://spectrum.library.concordia.ca/id/eprint/995478/1/Afrasiabi_PhD_S2024.pdf</etd_ms:identifier>
        <etd_ms:language>en</etd_ms:language><etd_ms:degree>
        <etd_ms:name>Ph. D.</etd_ms:name>
        <etd_ms:level>phd</etd_ms:level>
        <etd_ms:discipline>Electrical and Computer Engineering</etd_ms:discipline>
        <etd_ms:grantor>Concordia University</etd_ms:grantor></etd_ms:degree></etd_ms:thesis><etd_ms:thesis xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/ http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/etdms.xsd" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:etd_ms="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/">
        <etd_ms:title>Scaling up Machine Learning Models for fMRI Brain Encoding</etd_ms:title>
        <etd_ms:creator>Ahmadi, Sana</etd_ms:creator>
        <etd_ms:subject/>
        <etd_ms:description>This thesis investigates techniques for optimizing brain encoding models, emphasizing computational efficiency and the scalability of both data and models within the framework of large-scale functional magnetic resonance imaging (fMRI) datasets. Brain encoding aims to predict neural responses to complex stimuli, such as video frames, by utilizing latent feature representations from artificial neural networks. The first study explores the acceleration of
ridge regression, a widely used predictive model in brain encoding, particularly when applied to large fMRI datasets like the CNeuroMod Friends dataset. By implementing a novel batch-parallelization strategy using Dask, we achieved significant computational speedups of up to 33× with 8 compute nodes and 32 threads compared to a single-threaded scikit-learn.
The second study investigates how dataset size and model scaling affect brain encoding performance using vision Transformers. To do so, the VideoGPT model was trained end-to-end to extract spatiotemporal features from the Shinobi video game dataset with varying sample sizes (10K, 100K, 1M, and 6M) and model size (number of training parameters). Ridge regression is then used to predict brain activity based on fMRI data and the extracted features from video games. Our results show that larger datasets lead to significantly improved
encoding accuracy, with the 6M-sample dataset producing the highest Pearson correlation coefficients across subjects. Additionally, while increasing hidden layer dimensions in the transformer model greatly enhances performance, the number of attention heads appears to have a minimal effect. These findings emphasize the importance of data scaling for improving brain encoding, offering practical insights for optimizing neural network architectures in
the context of large-scale stimuli data.
This research advances the field of computationally efficient brain encoding, which is crucial for enhancing both computational speed and accuracy. These advancements are essential not only for improving our understanding of brain function but also for enabling scalable machine learning models on high-dimensional data and sophisticated stimuli, including applications
in neuroprosthetics and clinical neuroscience.</etd_ms:description>
        <etd_ms:publisher>Concordia University</etd_ms:publisher>
        <etd_ms:contributor role="advisor">Glatard, Tristan</etd_ms:contributor>
        <etd_ms:contributor role="advisor">Bellec, Pierre Lune</etd_ms:contributor>
        <etd_ms:date>2025-01-22</etd_ms:date>
        <etd_ms:type>Electronic Thesis or Dissertation</etd_ms:type>
        <etd_ms:identifier>TC-QMG-995062</etd_ms:identifier>
        <etd_ms:format>text</etd_ms:format>
        <etd_ms:identifier>https://spectrum.library.concordia.ca/id/eprint/995062/1/Ahmadi_PhD_F2025.pdf</etd_ms:identifier>
        <etd_ms:language>en</etd_ms:language><etd_ms:degree>
        <etd_ms:name>Ph. D.</etd_ms:name>
        <etd_ms:level>phd</etd_ms:level>
        <etd_ms:discipline>Computer Science</etd_ms:discipline>
        <etd_ms:grantor>Concordia University</etd_ms:grantor></etd_ms:degree></etd_ms:thesis><etd_ms:thesis xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/ http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/etdms.xsd" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:etd_ms="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/">
        <etd_ms:title>Low-Power Class-D Ampliﬁer for Industrial Applications</etd_ms:title>
        <etd_ms:creator>Aimaier, Nueraimaiti</etd_ms:creator>
        <etd_ms:subject>Class-D Amplifier; Pulse-Width Modulation.</etd_ms:subject>
        <etd_ms:description>This dissertation investigates the design and development of fully differential switching (class-D) amplifiers optimized for high efficiency, linearity, and compact integration, tailored to low-power applications such as industrial servo valves, hall effect sensors, and low-power actuators. These loads, commonly employed in automotive and other critical power systems, require differential sine wave inputs at frequencies ranging from several kilohertz to 10 kHz. Traditional linear amplifiers (Class A, B, and AB) are constrained by low efficiency and significant thermal management requirements, while switching amplifiers, despite their inherent efficiency advantages, pose challenges in mitigating nonlinearities and distortions.

The first major contribution is the development of a low-power Selective Harmonic Elimination Pulse-Width Modulation (SHEPWM)-based full-bridge inverter, featuring a novel FPGA hardware implementation. Unlike conventional SHEPWM systems focused on high-power, fixed-frequency applications (50 Hz–60 Hz), this work extends SHEPWM to low-power systems operating at high fundamental output frequencies (4 kHz–10 kHz). A unique FPGA-based architecture enables real-time configurability of output amplitude and frequency, offering flexibility without excessive computational or storage demands. Experimental results demonstrate harmonic elimination up to the 34th order, achieving total harmonic distortion (THD) below 5.1% and efficiency improvements of up to 17.3% compared to natural PWM (NPWM). By integrating this design into a compact system-in-package (SiP) utilizing Gallium-Nitride (GaN) power transistors, the inverter minimizes the printed circuit board (PCB) footprint compared to conventional discrete implementations. This integration offers a robust and versatile solution for next-generation low-power industry applications.

The second contribution is the design and analysis of a Double Integral Sliding Mode Control (DISMC)-based class-D amplifier. Theoretical work forms the foundation of this research, involving a rigorous analysis of reaching and stability conditions to derive optimal controller gains. The proposed controller employs a double-loop strategy that uses the integrals of inductor current and output voltage tracking errors to ensure robust tracking and stability under varying operating conditions. The theoretical findings are validated through extensive simulation and experimental studies, demonstrating the DISMC's superior disturbance rejection, enhanced transient response, and reliability compared to conventional proportional-integral (PI) controllers.

By combining innovative control techniques such as SHEPWM and DISMC with compact and efficient hardware designs, this research advances the state-of-the-art in switching amplifier technology. The outcomes offer practical solutions for compact, high-performance systems, addressing critical requirements in modern industrial applications while paving the way for future advancements in power electronics.</etd_ms:description>
        <etd_ms:publisher>Concordia University</etd_ms:publisher>
        <etd_ms:contributor role="advisor">Cowan, Glenn</etd_ms:contributor>
        <etd_ms:contributor role="advisor">Constantin, Nicolas</etd_ms:contributor>
        <etd_ms:date>2025-02-06</etd_ms:date>
        <etd_ms:type>Electronic Thesis or Dissertation</etd_ms:type>
        <etd_ms:identifier>TC-QMG-995444</etd_ms:identifier>
        <etd_ms:format>text</etd_ms:format>
        <etd_ms:identifier>https://spectrum.library.concordia.ca/id/eprint/995444/1/Aimaier_PhD_S2025.pdf</etd_ms:identifier>
        <etd_ms:language>en</etd_ms:language><etd_ms:degree>
        <etd_ms:name>Ph. D.</etd_ms:name>
        <etd_ms:level>phd</etd_ms:level>
        <etd_ms:discipline>Electrical and Computer Engineering</etd_ms:discipline>
        <etd_ms:grantor>Concordia University</etd_ms:grantor></etd_ms:degree></etd_ms:thesis><etd_ms:thesis xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/ http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/etdms.xsd" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:etd_ms="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/">
        <etd_ms:title>Religiopolitical Echo Chambers on Social Media in Shaping Pakistan’s Violent Extremism Discourse</etd_ms:title>
        <etd_ms:creator>Akram, Muhammad</etd_ms:creator>
        <etd_ms:subject>Facebook, Social Media, Pakistan, Radicalization, Extremism, Political, Religious, Religiopolitical, Narratives, Political Parties, Violence, Elections, Pakistan army, Pakistan Tehrik-e-Insaf, PTI, Tehrik Labbaik Pakistan, TLP.</etd_ms:subject>
        <etd_ms:description>Social media have emerged as a potent instrument for disseminating religiopolitical disinformation, inciting violent radicalism and extremism among youth. Young individuals are spending considerable time online, rendering them increasingly susceptible to radical propaganda aimed at political mobilization. This risk is heightened in societies with fragile political systems, where mainstream media lack credibility, and social media serves as the principal news source. This dissertation investigates the role of religiopolitical narratives on platforms such as Facebook in propagating violent radicalism among Pakistani youth and analyze how critical social media literacy (CSML) can mitigate or counteract online radical narratives.

This dissertation employs a manuscript-based approach with three interrelated sub-studies. The first sub-study systematically reviews how social media drives extremist discourse in Pakistan, setting the study’s context. The second sub-study examines CSML as a tool to counter radical propaganda, identifying key skills for prevention. Both systematic reviews use the PRISMA framework with peer-reviewed articles from Web of Science and Scopus databases. Finally, the third sub-study undertakes a critical ethnographic analysis in relation to the Pakistani youth’s perceptions and lived experiences about online discourses of radicalism and extremism. In-depth interviews were conducted with university students from diverse regions in Pakistan. Together, these studies use a thematic analysis approach and offer a comprehensive look at social media’s role in radicalism and how CSML can help combat it.

The sub-study 1 reveals that scholarship on social media’s role in violent extremism in Pakistan generally focuses on individual factors behind violent extremism, overlooking situational or political influences. The sub-study 2 highlights two key insights: Limited scholarship connects CSML to radicalism or extremism, yet CSML emerges as a promising educational countermeasure to prevent toxic narratives on social media. Pedagogies and curriculums should encourage and promote critical thinking abilities, as youth equipped with CSML skills are better positioned to safely navigate social media amid political disinformation. Ethnographic findings from sub-study 3 identify political interest groups and the military elite as major players who propagate radical religiopolitical narratives on Facebook, manipulating young users’ perceptions, electioneering, and political power. Such misuse of Facebook has fueled political violence, sectarianism, blasphemy cases, and distrust in institutions. Sub-study 3 also contextualizes how CSML could be a counter to prevent violent radicalism among Pakistani youth and mitigate the misuse of platforms like Facebook.

Overall, this dissertation argues that the political use and misuse of social media, particularly the widely popular Facebook, have complicated the already complex dynamics of radicalism and violent extremism in Pakistan. While these issues predate social media (e.g., anti-India and pro-Afghan jihad narratives), platforms like Facebook have amplified their reach and impact. The study shows how young people, often unwillingly, engage with competing radical narratives online, shaping their political ideologies, and sometimes justifying political violence. To address this, the study advocates for equipping Pakistani youth with CSML skills, enabling them to navigate social media safely and critically amidst the surge of radical religiopolitical narratives competing for attention.</etd_ms:description>
        <etd_ms:publisher>Concordia University</etd_ms:publisher>
        <etd_ms:contributor role="advisor">Arshad-Ayaz, Adeela</etd_ms:contributor>
        <etd_ms:date>2025-03-21</etd_ms:date>
        <etd_ms:type>Electronic Thesis or Dissertation</etd_ms:type>
        <etd_ms:identifier>TC-QMG-995267</etd_ms:identifier>
        <etd_ms:format>text</etd_ms:format>
        <etd_ms:identifier>https://spectrum.library.concordia.ca/id/eprint/995267/1/Akram_PhD_S2025.pdf</etd_ms:identifier>
        <etd_ms:language>en</etd_ms:language><etd_ms:degree>
        <etd_ms:name>Ph. D.</etd_ms:name>
        <etd_ms:level>phd</etd_ms:level>
        <etd_ms:discipline>Education</etd_ms:discipline>
        <etd_ms:grantor>Concordia University</etd_ms:grantor></etd_ms:degree></etd_ms:thesis><etd_ms:thesis xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/ http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/etdms.xsd" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:etd_ms="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/">
        <etd_ms:title>Advanced Blind Source Separation Methods for Multivariate Data Modeling and Clustering</etd_ms:title>
        <etd_ms:creator>Al-gumaei, Ali</etd_ms:creator>
        <etd_ms:subject/>
        <etd_ms:description>As the amount of data being generated keeps growing, there is an increasing demand for adaptable approaches that can effectively extract the overall trends while also maintaining subject-specific information from large-scale datasets. Modeling complex and high-dimensional data presents significant challenges across healthcare, human action recognition, and speech recognition.
In this dissertation, we develop a bounded multivariate generalized Gaussian mixture model (BMGGMM) integrated with independent component analysis (ICA) to effectively capture the correlated features in multivariate data. While independent vector analysis (IVA) extends ICA to handle multiple datasets by leveraging inter-dataset dependencies and preserving their correlation structures, it suffers from limitations when dealing with complex datasets. To overcome this, we propose a novel blind source separation (BSS) method that combines IVA with the BMGGMM framework, enabling robust modeling of complex data distributions with varying shapes and dimensions. Second, we introduced the integration of the ICA-BMGGMM and IVA-BMGGMM to the hidden Markov model (HMM) to boost their performance in terms of source separation. The performance of IVA deteriorates as the number of datasets and sources increases. To address this limitation, we propose the adaptive constrained IVA (acIVAMGGMM) and bounded acIVAMGGMM techniques. These methods integrate multiple reference signals into the IVA function and adaptively control the reference-estimated source relations. Finally, we introduce a new approach, ICA and IVA for common subspace analysis (ICABMGGMM-CS) and IVABMGGMM-CS, designed for the subspace analysis of multi-subject fMRI data. These methods leverage the strengths of both ICA and IVA while effectively addressing the challenges posed by high dimensions.</etd_ms:description>
        <etd_ms:publisher>Concordia University</etd_ms:publisher>
        <etd_ms:contributor role="advisor">Al-gumaei, Ali</etd_ms:contributor>
        <etd_ms:date>2025-01-13</etd_ms:date>
        <etd_ms:type>Electronic Thesis or Dissertation</etd_ms:type>
        <etd_ms:identifier>TC-QMG-995128</etd_ms:identifier>
        <etd_ms:format>text</etd_ms:format>
        <etd_ms:identifier>https://spectrum.library.concordia.ca/id/eprint/995128/1/Al-gumaei_PhD_W2025.pdf</etd_ms:identifier>
        <etd_ms:language>en</etd_ms:language><etd_ms:degree>
        <etd_ms:name>Ph. D.</etd_ms:name>
        <etd_ms:level>phd</etd_ms:level>
        <etd_ms:discipline>Information and Systems Engineering</etd_ms:discipline>
        <etd_ms:grantor>Concordia University</etd_ms:grantor></etd_ms:degree></etd_ms:thesis><etd_ms:thesis xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/ http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/etdms.xsd" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:etd_ms="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/">
        <etd_ms:title>Power-hardware-in-the-loop (PHIL) based Emulation of Faults in Induction Machines</etd_ms:title>
        <etd_ms:creator>Alla, Koteswara Rao</etd_ms:creator>
        <etd_ms:subject>doubly-fed induction generator (DFIG), dynamometer, emulation, induction machine (IM), inter-turn fault, locomotive, power-hardware-in-the-loop (PHIL), permanent magnet synchronous machine (PMSM),rotor inter-turn fault, voltage-behind-reactance (VBR), voltage-in and current-out (VICO), wound rotor induction machine (WRIM)</etd_ms:subject>
        <etd_ms:description>Induction motors (IMs) are commonly used motors because they are very rugged, require low maintenance, and are mechanically simple. The IM is the workhorse as a traction motor in rolling stock applications due to the inherent advantages in terms of cost, controllability, reliability, and maximum speed. An induction machine has three common faults: stator inter-turn faults, rotor broken bars, and bearing faults. These faults can affect the industry's productivity and cause outages in the transportation industry. For example, an induction motor failure in a freight locomotive can cause stalling and subsequent line congestion. Similarly, a wound rotor induction machine (WRIM) is used as a doubly fed induction generator (DFIG), the most commonly used topology for wind power applications.  The most common electrical faults in DFIG are bearing faults and inter-turn winding faults in the stator and rotor. If these faults are not detected and rectified in time, they can proliferate quickly and become catastrophic, leading to unexpected outages and contributing to high operating and maintenance costs. Hence, it is essential to study the behavior of WRIM’s in the event of these faults and what corrective action can be taken in the event of a fault. Also, it is necessary to investigate the faulted IM’s behavior with accurate models and replace expensive test benches and equipment with safer and economical test procedures.

There are a lot of practical difficulties in creating the fault with machines. Even if the fault is implemented, full voltage cannot always be applied, and motors with higher loads cannot be tested since it may damage the machine faster. However, a virtual machine with power electronic converters can be tested for different fault conditions using emulation. Power-hardware-in-loop (PHIL) based emulation is increasingly used as an economical test bench for testing the drive system. With PHIL-based emulation, the electrical machine is emulated in a laboratory environment with real-time power flow using power electronics converters. With PHIL-based emulation, the faulted machine behavior can be studied with direct online start or machines fed from variable frequency drives (VFD) without damaging the motor or VFD. With emulation, the risk, time, and cost associated with a physical machine subjected to faults can be reduced. Also, the emulation test setup is designed to return the power flow from the inverter to the mains supply. This requires an active front-end converter connected to the DC link of the emulator converter. Hence, only power losses are drawn from the power supply. Thus, the laboratory power supply requirements are reduced. 

The machine's mathematical model must be very accurate for better emulation accuracy. So, there is a need to develop detailed mathematical models which can account for the nonlinearities in the machine. The machine parameters vary when temperature changes. For an accurate emulation, it is necessary to consider the effect of temperature on the machine's behavior. For this, the thermal behavior of the machine is crucial. Lumped parameter thermal network (LPTN) models can be used for emulation purposes since finite element models (FEM) require long execution times which are not suitable for real-time emulation though it has higher accuracy.

This thesis investigates PHIL emulation of stator inter-turn faults and rotor inter-turn faults. Detailed and improved mathematical models for these faults are developed. An alternative mathematical model has been proposed for stator inter-turn faults, i.e., the Voltage-behind-reactance (VBR) model, which has some advantages compared to the conventional modeling approach of the voltage-in &amp; current-out (VICO) model.  Fault conditions are emulated with experimental hardware in real time. Emulation results are validated with a practical machine subjected to the faults. Thermal analysis of an induction machine with stator inter-turn fault is carried out. An analytical model is developed to estimate the temperature rise caused by the inter-turn fault, and the model is validated with experimental results.</etd_ms:description>
        <etd_ms:publisher>Concordia University</etd_ms:publisher>
        <etd_ms:contributor role="advisor">Pillay, Pragasen</etd_ms:contributor>
        <etd_ms:date>2025-04-24</etd_ms:date>
        <etd_ms:type>Electronic Thesis or Dissertation</etd_ms:type>
        <etd_ms:identifier>TC-QMG-995471</etd_ms:identifier>
        <etd_ms:format>text</etd_ms:format>
        <etd_ms:identifier>https://spectrum.library.concordia.ca/id/eprint/995471/1/Alla_PhD_S2025.pdf</etd_ms:identifier>
        <etd_ms:language>en</etd_ms:language><etd_ms:degree>
        <etd_ms:name>Ph. D.</etd_ms:name>
        <etd_ms:level>phd</etd_ms:level>
        <etd_ms:discipline>Electrical and Computer Engineering</etd_ms:discipline>
        <etd_ms:grantor>Concordia University</etd_ms:grantor></etd_ms:degree></etd_ms:thesis><etd_ms:thesis xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/ http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/etdms.xsd" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:etd_ms="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/">
        <etd_ms:title>Indoor Object Localization for Tracking and Progress Reporting in Construction</etd_ms:title>
        <etd_ms:creator>Bardareh, Hassan</etd_ms:creator>
        <etd_ms:subject/>
        <etd_ms:description>This research investigates the application of indoor object localization to enhance tracking and progress reporting in construction projects by automating the generation of onsite inspection reports and location identification of project  components. In this study, “inspection reports” refers to the documents used to monitor and record the progress of installed project components and track their target locations. Indoor object tracking is challenging due to the complex nature of construction environments, which typically are congested and contain many obstacles. Moreover, translating object-tracking information into meaningful progress reports is inherently challenging. To address these challenges, this study explores the integrated use of advanced technologies, such as RTLS and LiDAR, for location identification of the target objects. The study includes four main streams: (1) developing an object localization method based on integrated RTLS technologies and using trilateration techniques for 2D and 3D localization in indoor spaces, (2) integrating the object tracking with the progress tracking introducing MSI and QSI indices, and employing a cloud-based BIM platform for data collection and visualization, (3) integrating RTLS with point cloud data to refine the 3D object detection and localization functions, and (4) developing a digital-twin platform for automated generation of onsite inspection reports and visualization of the location and status of the objects associated with indoor construction operations. These reports are visualized through a bi-directional construction twin dashboard, facilitating ready access to progress-related information for site managers. The methods developed are validated through laboratory experiments and a case study conducted at a job site. In the laboratory experiments, the RTLS demonstrates an accuracy of approximately 0.52 m and 1.15 m, respectively, for 2D and 3D object localization. The 3D localization accuracy for the integrated RTLS and point cloud data, meanwhile, is found to be 27 cm. The case study also validates the effectiveness of the introduced indices in reporting the progress of the installation of components in mechanical rooms as part of a swimming pool construction project.</etd_ms:description>
        <etd_ms:publisher>Concordia University</etd_ms:publisher>
        <etd_ms:contributor role="advisor">Osama, Moselhi</etd_ms:contributor>
        <etd_ms:date>2025-02-05</etd_ms:date>
        <etd_ms:type>Electronic Thesis or Dissertation</etd_ms:type>
        <etd_ms:identifier>TC-QMG-995303</etd_ms:identifier>
        <etd_ms:format>text</etd_ms:format>
        <etd_ms:identifier>https://spectrum.library.concordia.ca/id/eprint/995303/1/Bardareh_PhD_S2025.pdf</etd_ms:identifier>
        <etd_ms:language>en</etd_ms:language><etd_ms:degree>
        <etd_ms:name>Ph. D.</etd_ms:name>
        <etd_ms:level>phd</etd_ms:level>
        <etd_ms:discipline>Building Engineering</etd_ms:discipline>
        <etd_ms:grantor>Concordia University</etd_ms:grantor></etd_ms:degree></etd_ms:thesis><etd_ms:thesis xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/ http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/etdms.xsd" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:etd_ms="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/">
        <etd_ms:title>Corporate Strategic Leadership and Hedge Fund Activism</etd_ms:title>
        <etd_ms:creator>Bazmohammadi, Saeid</etd_ms:creator>
        <etd_ms:subject>Shareholder activism; hedge fund activism; corporate governance; strategic leadership; chief executive officers; media; social evaluations; celebrity; infamy; media visibility; board gender diveristy; hostile resistance; power; political ideology; spillover effects</etd_ms:subject>
        <etd_ms:description>Over the past decades, activist hedge funds have come to the forefront of shareholder activism. Often viewed as proactive defenders of shareholder primacy, activist hedge funds acquire ownership stakes in corporations they perceive as mismanaged and advocate for changes to enhance shareholder value. This dissertation examines underexplored aspects of hedge fund activism through three essays, using a longitudinal dataset of companies listed in the Standard &amp; Poor’s (S&amp;P) 500 index between 2000 and 2020.
The first essay, grounded in corporate strategic leadership research, investigates whether social evaluations of CEOs—fame, celebrity, and infamy—affect the likelihood of their firms being targeted by activist hedge funds. Findings suggest that firms attract increased activist attention when their CEOs receive extensive media coverage, achieve celebrity status, or become infamous. I also find that this relationship is more substantial for firms led by female CEOs. 
The second essay explores the impact of hedge fund activism on board gender diversity in both targeted and non-targeted firms. Results indicate that activism is associated with declines in board gender diversity in targeted firms, and that this negative effect is mitigated when a celebrity CEO leads the company. Contrary to expectations, no evidence of spillover effects on non-targeted firms was found, and potential explanations for this finding are discussed.
The third essay examines why some firms respond to hedge fund activism with hostile resistance by adopting defensive governance provisions, such as shareholder rights plans. Drawing on upper echelons theory, I argue that CEOs’ political ideologies and power shape corporate resistance strategies against hedge fund targeting. Empirical findings partially support this argument, revealing a strong positive relationship between CEO power and the likelihood of hostile resistance.
Together, these essays contribute to the literature on shareholder activism and corporate strategic leadership, offering new insights into how CEO characteristics and governance dynamics shape firms’ interactions with activist hedge funds.</etd_ms:description>
        <etd_ms:publisher>Concordia University</etd_ms:publisher>
        <etd_ms:contributor role="advisor">Jeong, Young-Chul</etd_ms:contributor>
        <etd_ms:date>2025-02-04</etd_ms:date>
        <etd_ms:type>Electronic Thesis or Dissertation</etd_ms:type>
        <etd_ms:identifier>TC-QMG-995171</etd_ms:identifier>
        <etd_ms:format>text</etd_ms:format>
        <etd_ms:identifier>https://spectrum.library.concordia.ca/id/eprint/995171/1/Bazmohammadi_PhD_S2025.pdf</etd_ms:identifier>
        <etd_ms:language>en</etd_ms:language><etd_ms:degree>
        <etd_ms:name>Ph. D.</etd_ms:name>
        <etd_ms:level>phd</etd_ms:level>
        <etd_ms:discipline>Business Administration (Management specialization)</etd_ms:discipline>
        <etd_ms:grantor>Concordia University</etd_ms:grantor></etd_ms:degree></etd_ms:thesis><etd_ms:thesis xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/ http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/etdms.xsd" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:etd_ms="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/">
        <etd_ms:title>Listening to what matters most: A participatory action-based exploration of student perspectives with regards to the social aspects of school climate</etd_ms:title>
        <etd_ms:creator>Beaudoin, Jennifer</etd_ms:creator>
        <etd_ms:subject/>
        <etd_ms:description>Regarded as the soul of the school, embedded within community, safety, academics, and institutional environment, robust school climates are correlated with student engagement, achievement, and ultimately retention (National School Climate Center, 2024). Given the multifaceted nature of school climate, educational stakeholders wishing to embark on improvement initiatives benefit from practical direction with regards to the most effective and impactful course of action. By involving all stakeholders, including students, in the investigation of the social aspect of school climate, meaningful and sustainable growth is possible. The three studies included in the dissertation invited youth to interrogate three aspects of school climate: student-staff relationships, student behavior management, and student advocacy and empowerment in classroom and school-based decision-making. 
Study 1 examined the link between student-staff staff relationships and healthy school climates. Student participants equated heathy relationships staff as those which: 1) showed an interest in students outside of class; 2) managed their classrooms with equity and discretion; and 3) fostered redemption following infractions or conflict. It was determined that healthy student-staff relationships were the primary factor in creating healthy school climates which encourage student engagement and retention.   
Study 2 investigated youth perspectives with regards to how their behavior was managed and how this affected school climate. The findings showed that while the determinants of behavior are complex, engagement and behavior was heavily dependent on the adult students were interacting with. Practices which prevented infractions and minimized escalation included: 1) staff displaying care and concern for the whole student in and outside the school environment; 2) differentiated pedagogical practices which allow for student voice and choice; and 3) opportunities for redemption following infractions. It was concluded that strong school climates were ones that adopted restorative behavior management measures which addressed wrong-doing while protecting the integrity of all involved. 
Study 3 explored the relationship between school climate and the levels of student advocacy and empowerment in classroom and school-based decision-making. Again, it was concurred that strong school climates are ones which implicate students in classroom and school-based decision-making as much as possible. To respond to the severe lack of student advocacy opportunities at the high school level, Universal Design for Learning (UDL) practices which empower students to select their own learning modalities, pace, and evaluation protocols, was recommended for classrooms. As for implication in school-based decision-making, the creation of a student governance body was seen as a viable step to increase authentic student voice.   
Together the studies provide direction to educational stakeholders seeking an effective course of action to maximize student engagement. By prioritizing the social aspect of school climate (holistic student-staff relationships; restorative behavior management practices; and student voice and choice in classroom and school-based decision-making) school communities can, together, build sustainable school climates which address the complex needs of all stakeholders.</etd_ms:description>
        <etd_ms:publisher>Concordia University</etd_ms:publisher>
        <etd_ms:contributor role="advisor">D'Amico, Miranda</etd_ms:contributor>
        <etd_ms:date>2025-03-19</etd_ms:date>
        <etd_ms:type>Electronic Thesis or Dissertation</etd_ms:type>
        <etd_ms:identifier>TC-QMG-995167</etd_ms:identifier>
        <etd_ms:format>text</etd_ms:format>
        <etd_ms:identifier>https://spectrum.library.concordia.ca/id/eprint/995167/1/Beaudoin_PhD_S2025_.pdf</etd_ms:identifier>
        <etd_ms:language>en</etd_ms:language><etd_ms:degree>
        <etd_ms:name>Ph. D.</etd_ms:name>
        <etd_ms:level>phd</etd_ms:level>
        <etd_ms:discipline>Education</etd_ms:discipline>
        <etd_ms:grantor>Concordia University</etd_ms:grantor></etd_ms:degree></etd_ms:thesis><etd_ms:thesis xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/ http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/etdms.xsd" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:etd_ms="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/">
        <etd_ms:title>Hub-line location problems with elastic demands and their application in the design of urban mobility hubs</etd_ms:title>
        <etd_ms:creator>Cobeña, Brenda</etd_ms:creator>
        <etd_ms:subject/>
        <etd_ms:description>Nowadays, urban transportation networks face challenges such as a rapid increase in urban population, city sprawl, and the use of private vehicles. To guarantee adequate mobility, it is crucial to develop efficient public transportation networks. In this thesis we focus our attention in the design of hub-line location problems (HLLP) to address the problems of designing efficient public transit networks.
First, we present an extension of the HLLP where we integrate gravity models to incorporate demand elasticity into an optimization model. This extension is denoted as the profit-oriented hub line location problem with elastic demand (ED-HLLP). We propose mixed-integer formulations, including a nonlinear mathematical model, and a path-based linear model. The linear formulations assign variables to each possible in the hub-line. A smart enumeration mechanism is provided to create all possible candidate paths. Finally, we also present a computational experience that evaluates the strengths and limits of these formulations.
Second, we introduce a column generation-based algorithm and a hybrid matheuristic that combines column generation with local search to address the ED-HLLP for large-sized problems, to better cope with the combinatorial nature of the number variable of the linear model. Computational experiments show that the proposed approaches are more robust and provide optimal and near-optimal solutions for all problems in our study when compared to the method introduced in ED-HLLP. Furthermore, we conduct a case study in the metropolitan area of Montreal to show the applicability and relevance of the proposed heuristic in a real-world context.
Third, we further extend the ED-HLLP to incorporate additional decisions on the services provided at the hub-nodes. We assume that the demand model is sensitive to both travel times, and quality of service, and our optimization model aims at maximizing the total profit derived from time savings while offering enhanced mobility services. A mixed-integer programming formulation is proposed, and a case study in Montreal is conducted to show the effectiveness of the proposed model.</etd_ms:description>
        <etd_ms:publisher>Concordia University</etd_ms:publisher>
        <etd_ms:contributor role="advisor">Contardo, Claudio</etd_ms:contributor>
        <etd_ms:date>2025-02-02</etd_ms:date>
        <etd_ms:type>Electronic Thesis or Dissertation</etd_ms:type>
        <etd_ms:identifier>TC-QMG-995247</etd_ms:identifier>
        <etd_ms:format>text</etd_ms:format>
        <etd_ms:identifier>https://spectrum.library.concordia.ca/id/eprint/995247/1/Cobena_PhD_S2025.pdf</etd_ms:identifier>
        <etd_ms:language>en</etd_ms:language><etd_ms:degree>
        <etd_ms:name>Ph. D.</etd_ms:name>
        <etd_ms:level>phd</etd_ms:level>
        <etd_ms:discipline>Industrial Engineering</etd_ms:discipline>
        <etd_ms:grantor>Concordia University</etd_ms:grantor></etd_ms:degree></etd_ms:thesis><etd_ms:thesis xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/ http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/etdms.xsd" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:etd_ms="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/">
        <etd_ms:title>Naming the Traces: (Re)Constructing and Irish-Canadian Family Narrative of Emigration, Place-Making, and Return</etd_ms:title>
        <etd_ms:creator>Drukker, Kelly Norah</etd_ms:creator>
        <etd_ms:subject>oral history; memory studies; space and place; cultural geography; Irish studies; place-making; family narratives; creative nonfiction; emigration; Point St. Charles; photography; memory work; intimate ethnography; Irish emigration; Montreal; family history; material culture; walking interview; mobile methodology; psychogeography; place; 20th century history; return-migration; women's life narratives; women's studies; life writing; memoir; Shrule, Ireland; anglophone Quebec; the Irish in Quebec; oral history interviews; intergenerational interviews; walking as methodology; working-class history; public history; unmarried mothers; emplaced memories; family interviews; essay of place; memory text; women's narratives; auto/biography; research-creation, Irish diaspora, the Irish in Canada.</etd_ms:subject>
        <etd_ms:description>This dissertation, conceived within the research-creation stream of Concordia University’s interdisciplinary Humanities program, considers the spatial, social, emotional, and cultural journey of emigration, place-making, and return-migration that the last four generations of my maternal family have undertaken between Ireland and Montreal, Canada from the late 1920s to the present day. Drawing from the fields of Oral History and Narrative, Memory Studies, Irish Studies, and Creative Nonfiction (studio component), this project begins by reconstructing the circumstances surrounding my maternal great-grandmother Norah’s emigration from her home in County Mayo, Ireland to Montreal, Quebec where she raised my grandmother Rose as a single mother during the Great Depression. The narrative then follows the subsequent generations of my family, and their emplaced memories in Montreal: from Rose’s upbringing in a series of downtown rooming-houses, to my mother and uncles’ childhood among the laneways and cold-water flats of the working-class neighborhood of Point St. Charles in the 1950s and ‘60s. The project concludes with an essay of place that recounts my experience of visiting my great-grandmother’s home-place in Shrule parish, as the first member of my family to “return” since emigration. To recreate the life-worlds of my family’s past, I draw upon oral history interviews with family members, including the mobile methodology of the walking interview; primary sources, such as ships’ records, photographs, and memory objects; secondary sources to contextualize my family’s experiences; and on-site explorations in Montreal and Ireland. Recounted in a narrative voice that blends description, analysis, and reflection, my dissertation situates itself at the intersection of what cultural historian Annette Kuhn calls “memory work”; “intimate ethnography,” a term coined by Alisse Waterston and Barbara Rylko-Bauer; and creative nonfiction.</etd_ms:description>
        <etd_ms:publisher>Concordia University</etd_ms:publisher>
        <etd_ms:contributor role="advisor">Lorenzkowski, Barbara</etd_ms:contributor>
        <etd_ms:date>2025-01-12</etd_ms:date>
        <etd_ms:type>Electronic Thesis or Dissertation</etd_ms:type>
        <etd_ms:identifier>TC-QMG-995000</etd_ms:identifier>
        <etd_ms:format>text</etd_ms:format>
        <etd_ms:identifier>https://spectrum.library.concordia.ca/id/eprint/995000/1/Drukker_PhD_S2025.pdf</etd_ms:identifier>
        <etd_ms:language>en</etd_ms:language><etd_ms:degree>
        <etd_ms:name>Ph. D.</etd_ms:name>
        <etd_ms:level>phd</etd_ms:level>
        <etd_ms:discipline>Humanities</etd_ms:discipline>
        <etd_ms:grantor>Concordia University</etd_ms:grantor></etd_ms:degree></etd_ms:thesis><etd_ms:thesis xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/ http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/etdms.xsd" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:etd_ms="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/">
        <etd_ms:title>Advancing Cybersecurity in Power Grids with High Penetration of Wind Energy: From Modeling to Mitigation of Cyberattacks against Wind Farms</etd_ms:title>
        <etd_ms:creator>Du, Hang</etd_ms:creator>
        <etd_ms:subject>research-creation</etd_ms:subject>
        <etd_ms:description>The increasing integration of wind energy and the reliance on digital communication systems for the remote operation of wind farms (WFs) have significantly expanded the grid’s vulnerability to cyberattacks. These risks are particularly concerning for power grids with degrading system strength (SS) and high penetration of converter-based resources, where cyber-induced instabilities threaten grid stability. This thesis investigates critical aspects of cyber risks in wind-integrated power grids, focusing on attack modeling and prevention, risk management, and mitigation strategies.
The first part introduces a cyberattack model targeting SS provision to permanent magnet synchronous generator (PMSG)-based WFs. To address this, an anomalous command verification (ACV) module is proposed to detect and prevent cyber-induced converter-driven instabilities by estimating SS buffer capacity. The second part develops a cyber-informed risk management framework using Bayesian attack graphs and distributionally robust optimization (DRO) to quantify and mitigate cyber risks. This framework incorporates converter-driven stability support (CDSS) from WFs and is validated on the IEEE 118-bus system. The third part focuses on mitigating attack-induced instabilities in offshore wind farms (OWFs) connected via High Voltage Direct Current (HVDC) systems. It introduces a physics-informed iterative control (PIC) strategy based on neural networks to reduce instability magnitudes progressively.
These contributions provide an integrated approach to addressing cyber risks in wind-integrated power grids, enhancing their security and stability in the face of evolving threats.</etd_ms:description>
        <etd_ms:publisher>Concordia University</etd_ms:publisher>
        <etd_ms:contributor role="advisor">Yan, Jun</etd_ms:contributor>
        <etd_ms:contributor role="advisor">Debbabi, Mourad</etd_ms:contributor>
        <etd_ms:date>2025-03-02</etd_ms:date>
        <etd_ms:type>Electronic Thesis or Dissertation</etd_ms:type>
        <etd_ms:identifier>TC-QMG-995096</etd_ms:identifier>
        <etd_ms:format>text</etd_ms:format>
        <etd_ms:identifier>https://spectrum.library.concordia.ca/id/eprint/995096/1/Hang_PhD_S2025.pdf</etd_ms:identifier>
        <etd_ms:language>en</etd_ms:language><etd_ms:degree>
        <etd_ms:name>Ph. D.</etd_ms:name>
        <etd_ms:level>phd</etd_ms:level>
        <etd_ms:discipline>Information and Systems Engineering</etd_ms:discipline>
        <etd_ms:grantor>Concordia University</etd_ms:grantor></etd_ms:degree></etd_ms:thesis><etd_ms:thesis xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/ http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/etdms.xsd" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:etd_ms="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/">
        <etd_ms:title>The Challenges and Enablers of Maker-Centered Learning Experiences
in Formal Education</etd_ms:title>
        <etd_ms:creator>Duponsel, Nathalie</etd_ms:creator>
        <etd_ms:subject>maker-centered education, maker-centered learning experiences, Maker Movement, formal education, challenges and enablers</etd_ms:subject>
        <etd_ms:description>Maker-centered education, inspired by the Maker Movement, has gained popularity in schools for its creative, hands-on approach, yet its integration into formal K-12 settings remains complex and underexplored. This thesis investigates key challenges and enablers for teachers in adopting maker-centered education by investigating the challenges reported in the current K-12 literature, the factors experienced maker-centered educators perceive influence teachers’ ability to integrate maker-centered education into K-12 formal education settings, and the potential learning outcomes of an interdisciplinary maker-centered learning experience in the context of higher education. 

This thesis presents three manuscripts. Manuscript 1 reports the results of a scoping review that identified 105 studies reporting challenges in maker-centered education integration in 10 primary areas. Findings revealed that although one third of studies mentioned challenges, most lacked detailed explanations. Notably, challenges varied based on educators’ level of experience with maker-centered education; however, only a minority of studies that identified challenges involved experienced teachers in maker-centered education. These findings highlight the need for further research with experienced educators of maker-centered education to better understand these challenges.

Manuscript 2, a qualitative study involving 21 educators with maker-centered education experience, provided insights into both known and newly identified challenges, together with factors that facilitate integration. The findings highlighted the need for further research in each of the challenge areas, particularly regarding learning outcomes of maker-centered education as some remain unconvinced of its learning potential.

In manuscript 3, I document a maker-centered learning experience in which I participated during my doctoral program that resulted in publishable scientific findings, contributing valuable evidence toward the educational benefits of maker-centered education.

This thesis reveals numerous educator-perceived challenges when implementing maker-centered education, underscoring the need for a structured approach for successful integration of maker-centered education programs in formal education settings. With a greater understanding of these factors, the Guiding Questions Framework for Developing a Maker-Centered Education Program and a set of recommendations were developed to help education leaders and educators develop and implement maker-centered education programs in formal education settings so that students can benefit from its many affordances.</etd_ms:description>
        <etd_ms:publisher>Concordia University</etd_ms:publisher>
        <etd_ms:contributor role="advisor">Davidson, Ann-Louise</etd_ms:contributor>
        <etd_ms:date>2025-02-27</etd_ms:date>
        <etd_ms:type>Electronic Thesis or Dissertation</etd_ms:type>
        <etd_ms:identifier>TC-QMG-995438</etd_ms:identifier>
        <etd_ms:format>text</etd_ms:format>
        <etd_ms:identifier>https://spectrum.library.concordia.ca/id/eprint/995438/1/DELAHAYEDUPONSEL_PhD_S2025.pdf</etd_ms:identifier>
        <etd_ms:language>en</etd_ms:language><etd_ms:degree>
        <etd_ms:name>Ph. D.</etd_ms:name>
        <etd_ms:level>phd</etd_ms:level>
        <etd_ms:discipline>Education</etd_ms:discipline>
        <etd_ms:grantor>Concordia University</etd_ms:grantor></etd_ms:degree></etd_ms:thesis><etd_ms:thesis xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/ http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/etdms.xsd" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:etd_ms="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/">
        <etd_ms:title>Producing and Valorizing Industrial Animal Waste: Climate Change Related Disasters and Waste-to-Energy Projects</etd_ms:title>
        <etd_ms:creator>Eccles, Stephanie Mary Rose</etd_ms:creator>
        <etd_ms:subject/>
        <etd_ms:description>As consensus sharpens regarding the socioecological and climate harms perpetuated by industrial capitalist animal agriculture, corporate-driven, 
government-subsidized efforts intensify. In this dissertation, I examine the role of industrial animal wastes in these efforts, analyzing how waste management practices function as accumulation strategies. I draw from interviews and fieldwork conducted in North Carolina and British Columbia and insights from political ecology, agrarian studies, waste studies, and animal geographies. This manuscript-based dissertation centers industrial animal waste management practices in the context of the agricultural industry framed as both a victim of and contributor to the climate crisis. I examine how waste-to-energy projects convert biowaste into contested renewable energy through anaerobic digesters. In North
Carolina, unwavering government support enables the pig industry to capitalize on the energy transition. By tracing the political developments that fostered the alliance between “Big Agriculture” and “Big Energy,” this research argues that biogas projects perpetuate patterns of uneven racialized development. These patterns are evident in the legacies of the sprayfield lagoon system and the Smithfield Agreement, where efforts to phase-out these waste systems were undermined in favour of extracting value. Central to this process is the systemic devaluation of the bodies, environments, and futures of racialized, Indigenous, and low-income
communities. In addition, I explore the production and management of industrial animal waste during climate change-related disasters. I argue that waste management logic, informed by confinement practices, shapes disaster governance. Institutional policies disincentivize mitigation, rewarding inaction through disaster relief mechanisms. Specifically, I engage with the emergence of post-disaster waste economies and processes, where value is derived from the decomposing bodies of farmed animals through the recovery of energy and nutrients. Together,
these findings highlight the persistence of agricultural exceptionalism, which entrenches industrial practices and delays the adoption of socially just, sustainable practices, particularly by situating it as an emerging key player in the energy transition. This dissertation demonstrates how industrial animal agriculture's waste management strategies intersect with environmental injustice, energy transitions, and climate-induced disasters, underscoring the need for interdisciplinary research and cross-movement organizing to resist the entrenchment and expansion of industrial animal agriculture through waste frontiers.</etd_ms:description>
        <etd_ms:publisher>Concordia University</etd_ms:publisher>
        <etd_ms:contributor role="advisor">Turner, Sarah</etd_ms:contributor>
        <etd_ms:contributor role="advisor">Stoddard, Elisabeth</etd_ms:contributor>
        <etd_ms:date>2025-01-09</etd_ms:date>
        <etd_ms:type>Electronic Thesis or Dissertation</etd_ms:type>
        <etd_ms:identifier>TC-QMG-995106</etd_ms:identifier>
        <etd_ms:format>text</etd_ms:format>
        <etd_ms:identifier>https://spectrum.library.concordia.ca/id/eprint/995106/1/Eccles_PhD_W2025.pdf</etd_ms:identifier>
        <etd_ms:language>en</etd_ms:language><etd_ms:degree>
        <etd_ms:name>Ph. D.</etd_ms:name>
        <etd_ms:level>phd</etd_ms:level>
        <etd_ms:discipline>Geography, Urban &amp; Environmental Studies</etd_ms:discipline>
        <etd_ms:grantor>Concordia University</etd_ms:grantor></etd_ms:degree></etd_ms:thesis><etd_ms:thesis xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/ http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/etdms.xsd" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:etd_ms="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/">
        <etd_ms:title>Of Tables, Tongues, and Pineapples: Visualising the Sense of Taste in Early Modern Dutch Still Life and Natural Philosophy</etd_ms:title>
        <etd_ms:creator>Enríquez Vázquez, Laura Eliza</etd_ms:creator>
        <etd_ms:subject/>
        <etd_ms:description>In The Art of Painting (Amsterdam 1707), the Dutch artist and writer Gérard de Lairesse (1641-1711) stated that the sense of taste “cannot be painted ; but may be in some measure expressed by occult significations.” During the early modern period, European subjectivities came in contact with “new” foods and flavours that they had not experienced before. In order to make these experiences intelligible, they embarked on a journey for visualising the invisible. This dissertation explores the multiple strategies adopted by Dutch artists and natural philosophers to visualise the sense of taste.  

Drawing from the fields of sensory studies, and the interconnected histories of art and knowledge, this project aims at investigating the role of the sense of taste in late seventeenth-century and early eighteenth-century Dutch art from a global perspective. It explores early modern ideas about taste and sense perception, and their role in art theory and scientific discourses on nature and the body. Modelling subjectivity and shaping society, the sense of taste was conceived within a larger project of nation-building and world-making. 

Looking across a variety of visual genres and media, this dissertation proposes an iconography of the sense of taste that encompasses allegories of the five senses, still life, and scientific illustration. It looks at these images in light of an array of textual sources, including art theory, travel literature, natural philosophy, and culinary recipes. In order to do so, it considers three different case studies: Gérard de Lairesse’s views on still life and the five senses; the tongue in anatomical illustration; and, finally, the global history of the pineapple as the epitome of taste and the ineffable.</etd_ms:description>
        <etd_ms:publisher>Concordia University</etd_ms:publisher>
        <etd_ms:contributor role="advisor">Howes, David</etd_ms:contributor>
        <etd_ms:date>2025-01-29</etd_ms:date>
        <etd_ms:type>Electronic Thesis or Dissertation</etd_ms:type>
        <etd_ms:identifier>TC-QMG-995360</etd_ms:identifier>
        <etd_ms:format>text</etd_ms:format>
        <etd_ms:identifier>https://spectrum.library.concordia.ca/id/eprint/995360/7/Enriquez_PhD_S2025.pdf</etd_ms:identifier>
        <etd_ms:language>en</etd_ms:language><etd_ms:degree>
        <etd_ms:name>Ph. D.</etd_ms:name>
        <etd_ms:level>phd</etd_ms:level>
        <etd_ms:discipline>Humanities</etd_ms:discipline>
        <etd_ms:grantor>Concordia University</etd_ms:grantor></etd_ms:degree></etd_ms:thesis><etd_ms:thesis xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/ http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/etdms.xsd" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:etd_ms="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/">
        <etd_ms:title>An Artistic and Performative Decoding and Encoding of International Law for the Posthuman Cyborg Anthropocene</etd_ms:title>
        <etd_ms:creator>Fitzgerald, Oonagh Elizabeth</etd_ms:creator>
        <etd_ms:subject/>
        <etd_ms:description>This dissertation describes the development of my transdisciplinary international law-arts research-creation (TILARC) practice for decoding and encoding international law through art and performance. This practice is based on a critique of the body of international law that developed from the 1945 Charter of the United Nations. It uses art and performance to imagine renewing this planetary charter to address the environmental, technological, humanitarian and human rights challenges of our times. This is not a law reform project, but an imaginative and creative project aimed at engaging a broader audience in thinking and making art and performance about international law relevant to contemporary crises.

TILARC was developed from my desire to make art and performance while contemplating international law unbounded by the confines of legal practice. It is a reflective practice of decoding international law and a creative practice of encoding values more suited to addressing contemporary challenges. The dissertation provides an overview of the international law system and identifies its defects and potential for addressing contemporary issues. Through diffractive reading of critical literature about the language of law and international law’s foundations, and cultural and philosophical critiques, the dissertation explores how law interacts with the crises of the posthuman cyborg anthropocene. 

Fuelled by these insights, research-creation provides a thoughtful, embodied means to explore and deepen transdisciplinary practice, by mingling artmaking, performance and law in a continuous productive flow. Autoethnography, grounded theory, practice-led research, critical studies and relativism provide ethical guidance for developing experiential, data-driven, performative, embodied knowledge combining the arts and international law. 

The dissertation documents TILARC projects of reimagining through art and performance values that are more suited for our times. These include exploring identity through painting masks; using sketching to reflect on war and peace; artivism, artmaking and lawmaking to envision a future without plastic pollution; and political, academic and artistic projects seeking to uncover and encode shared values to support collaborative co-creation. TILARC produces practical and scholarly contributions to knowledge about how the arts can be used to gain deeper understanding of international law problems and strengthen individual agency in seeking to contribute creatively to possible solutions.</etd_ms:description>
        <etd_ms:publisher>Concordia University</etd_ms:publisher>
        <etd_ms:contributor role="advisor">Tsabart, Eldad</etd_ms:contributor>
        <etd_ms:date>2025-02-06</etd_ms:date>
        <etd_ms:type>Electronic Thesis or Dissertation</etd_ms:type>
        <etd_ms:identifier>TC-QMG-995229</etd_ms:identifier>
        <etd_ms:format>text</etd_ms:format>
        <etd_ms:identifier>https://spectrum.library.concordia.ca/id/eprint/995229/5/Fitzgerald_PhD_S2025.pdf</etd_ms:identifier>
        <etd_ms:language>en</etd_ms:language>
        <etd_ms:format>image</etd_ms:format>
        <etd_ms:identifier>https://spectrum.library.concordia.ca/id/eprint/995229/2/Fitzgerald_PhD_S2025_Annex%20VII%20Figures%20Part%20I%20or%20III%20.pdf</etd_ms:identifier>
        <etd_ms:language>en</etd_ms:language>
        <etd_ms:format>image</etd_ms:format>
        <etd_ms:identifier>https://spectrum.library.concordia.ca/id/eprint/995229/3/Fitzgerald_PhD_S2025_Annex%20VII%20Figures%20Part%20II%20of%20III%20.pdf</etd_ms:identifier>
        <etd_ms:language>en</etd_ms:language>
        <etd_ms:format>image</etd_ms:format>
        <etd_ms:identifier>https://spectrum.library.concordia.ca/id/eprint/995229/4/Fitzgerald_PhD_S2025_Annex%20VII%20Figures%20Part%20III%20of%20III%20.pdf</etd_ms:identifier>
        <etd_ms:language>en</etd_ms:language><etd_ms:degree>
        <etd_ms:name>Ph. D.</etd_ms:name>
        <etd_ms:level>phd</etd_ms:level>
        <etd_ms:discipline>Individualized Program</etd_ms:discipline>
        <etd_ms:grantor>Concordia University</etd_ms:grantor></etd_ms:degree></etd_ms:thesis><etd_ms:thesis xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/ http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/etdms.xsd" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:etd_ms="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/">
        <etd_ms:title>Vision-Based Construction Activity Recognition Using Supervised and Self-Supervised Methods</etd_ms:title>
        <etd_ms:creator>Ghelmani Rashid Abad, Ali</etd_ms:creator>
        <etd_ms:subject/>
        <etd_ms:description>Tracking and monitoring the activities of construction entities, such as workers and equipment, on construction sites is crucial for assessing their performance and productivity. However, manual monitoring is demanding, time-consuming, and susceptible to inaccuracies. To this end, numerous automated computer vision (CV)-based methods have been developed to detect construction entities and classify their activities. Recently, single-stage activity recognition methods that simultaneously analyze spatial and temporal information have been proposed in the construction domain. While these methods have demonstrated improved performance over multi-stage approaches and can alleviate their limitations, they still suffer from a significant drawback: relatively low per-frame activity recognition and localization accuracy. This limitation necessitates additional post-processing to link the per-frame detection results and construct the corresponding action tubes, which in turn reduces the real-time applicability of these methods for simultaneous detection of the activities of multiple construction entities. 
Another major disadvantage of the current state-of-the-art construction equipment activity recognition methods is their reliance on supervised learning. This approach requires large, labeled datasets for each type of equipment and activity, which can be costly and time-consuming to create. Particularly, for the task of activity recognition and localization that requires frame-level annotations. To address this challenge, many self-supervised deep learning methods have been proposed in the CV domain, which exploit the abundant unlabeled data to alleviate the data annotation cost by creating labels from the input data itself. However, the assumption of availability of abundant unlabeled data limits the applicability of the current self-supervised methods in the construction domain in which the number of videos for various activities of different construction equipment is also limited. 
To overcome the aforementioned limitations, parallel frameworks are proposed in this research for developing a general construction entity activity recognition method. As such, the main objectives of this research are: (1) to tackle the data annotation requirements of existing supervised methods by utilizing Self-Supervised Learning (SSL) to leverage the information available in the unlabeled construction site videos; (2) to develop and apply an SSL method specifically tailored to limited-data scenarios in the construction domain, in contrast to the SSL methods developed in the CV domain that depend on the availability of abundant unlabeled data; (3) to develop a supervised, single-stage construction equipment activity recognition and localization method with high per-frame performance, thus, removing the need for a post-processing step; (4) to improve the activity recognition and localization performance for complex and fast-paced activities (e.g., excavator swinging) by incorporating the dynamic information present in the temporal gradient data modality of input videos, combined with knowledge distillation, to improve per-frame performance without increasing inference computation; (5) to enhance the multi-scale and generalization performance of the supervised method developed in the third objective through the development of a custom pyramid architecture and a novel anchor-free localization method; and (6) to provide accurate, real-time activity recognition and localization information of a diverse set of construction entities with significant size differences. 
It is found that the developed SSL method results in an improvement of 10.1% over its supervised counterpart when using only 5% of the labels in the dataset. As such, the results clearly indicate the potential of the proposed SSL method for improving the model performance at no additional data annotation cost. Furthermore, the developed supervised single-stage method achieved per-frame excavator activity recognition and localization accuracies of 93.6% and 79.8%, respectively, thus eliminating the need for post-processing. This method was further enhanced to provide accurate, consistent, and real-time performance for simultaneous activity recognition and localization of construction entities with significant scale variations. Notably, it attained per-frame activity recognition accuracy of 94.67% and localization accuracy of 87.35% for simultaneous recognition of excavators and workers’ activities, despite their substantial size differences. Consequently, the obtained results demonstrate the effectiveness and applicability of the developed method at providing real-time monitoring information.</etd_ms:description>
        <etd_ms:publisher>Concordia University</etd_ms:publisher>
        <etd_ms:contributor role="advisor">Hammad, Amin</etd_ms:contributor>
        <etd_ms:date>2025-02-11</etd_ms:date>
        <etd_ms:type>Electronic Thesis or Dissertation</etd_ms:type>
        <etd_ms:identifier>TC-QMG-995345</etd_ms:identifier>
        <etd_ms:format>text</etd_ms:format>
        <etd_ms:identifier>https://spectrum.library.concordia.ca/id/eprint/995345/1/GhelmaniRashidAbad_PhD_S2025.pdf</etd_ms:identifier>
        <etd_ms:language>en</etd_ms:language><etd_ms:degree>
        <etd_ms:name>Ph. D.</etd_ms:name>
        <etd_ms:level>phd</etd_ms:level>
        <etd_ms:discipline>Information and Systems Engineering</etd_ms:discipline>
        <etd_ms:grantor>Concordia University</etd_ms:grantor></etd_ms:degree></etd_ms:thesis><etd_ms:thesis xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/ http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/etdms.xsd" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:etd_ms="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/">
        <etd_ms:title>From Photography and Walking to Walking and Photography</etd_ms:title>
        <etd_ms:creator>Guillaume, Philippe</etd_ms:creator>
        <etd_ms:subject/>
        <etd_ms:description>This dissertation examines the link between photographs taken by photographers who walk to
take pictures and walking artists who take pictures as a visual record of their art. The
interconnection between photography and walking underwent a major reconfiguration in the
1960s when walking became an autonomous form of art while, at virtually the same moment,
American, British, and European street photographers were walking to produce documentary
photographs injected with a new subjective approach. My research program was initiated at Tate
Archives where a messy snapshot taken in 1967 by Hamish Fulton drew my thinking into sharp
focus. Here was the inception of walking as art in a street photograph. This snapshot is given
close visual analysis as the central photographic document for this thesis. A conversation with
Fulton concentrated on this picture, which had laid dormant for four decades. Close visual
analysis of this photograph sets the direction of the thesis toward qualitative investigation,
underpinned by historical findings and theoretical insight. This methodology is applied to select
photos and art projects from the 1960s to the near present. Genres include street photography,
conceptual art, performance art and land art. This thesis is structured around a dual perspective of
photography/walking as well as walking/photography. It offers new insight into the
interdependency of photography and walking and argues that this relationship underwent a major
change and institutional challenge around 1967. My study has been enriched by my interaction
with a network of walking artists and my own research-practice.</etd_ms:description>
        <etd_ms:publisher>Concordia University</etd_ms:publisher>
        <etd_ms:contributor role="advisor">Langford, Martha</etd_ms:contributor>
        <etd_ms:date>2025-01-09</etd_ms:date>
        <etd_ms:type>Electronic Thesis or Dissertation</etd_ms:type>
        <etd_ms:identifier>TC-QMG-995243</etd_ms:identifier>
        <etd_ms:format>text</etd_ms:format>
        <etd_ms:identifier>https://spectrum.library.concordia.ca/id/eprint/995243/1/Guillaume_PhD_S2025.pdf</etd_ms:identifier>
        <etd_ms:language>en</etd_ms:language><etd_ms:degree>
        <etd_ms:name>Ph. D.</etd_ms:name>
        <etd_ms:level>phd</etd_ms:level>
        <etd_ms:discipline>Art History</etd_ms:discipline>
        <etd_ms:grantor>Concordia University</etd_ms:grantor></etd_ms:degree></etd_ms:thesis><etd_ms:thesis xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/ http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/etdms.xsd" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:etd_ms="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/">
        <etd_ms:title>Navigating Difference in the Shadow of War: A Local History of Identity Formation after Political Mass Violence in Zvornik County</etd_ms:title>
        <etd_ms:creator>Hackley, Kevin</etd_ms:creator>
        <etd_ms:subject/>
        <etd_ms:description>As was the case in numerous localities in the Independent State of Croatia, the civilians of Zvornik County in Bosnia and Herzegovina were subjected to collective mass violence committed by various military actors during the Second World War. This dissertation uses testimonies gathered by the Communist Party of Yugoslavia (Komunistička partija Jugoslavije – KPJ) in their “Territorial Commission for Determining the Crimes of the Occupiers and their Collaborators of Bosnia and Herzegovina” to dissect the nature of political mass violence in Zvornik. Local Ustaša began arresting Serbian political and religious elites as early as the summer of 1941, escalating further in August during a country-wide campaign to capture and expel Serbs living in the country to German-occupied Serbia. Often motivated by revenge for crimes against Serbian civilians, Četnik units responded with violence against Muslim communities, a group that was collectively identified with the Ustaša regime and their policies.  

Using monthly reports submitted by the County Committee for the KPJ stationed in Zvornik, this project analyzes the impact of the conflict on how the residents of Zvornik (Zvorničani) defined their relationships to the group categories of “Serbian” and “Muslim” in the immediate postwar period. It is argued that the grievances from crimes committed during the Second World War exacerbated the perceived separateness of these identities. 

Moreover, while the national Party platform of the KPJ celebrated the diversity of Yugoslavia and the Republic of Bosnia and Herzegovina, the execution of several policies, particularly those related to the policing of Islam, fueled greater disharmony between groups. In the case of Zvornik County, this problem was made worse by the antagonistic behavior and incompetence of local KPJ officials. This not only affected the legitimacy of Party institutions and policies in Zvornik, but also generated more distrust between Muslims and Serbs. It is only through this kind of micro-level data and analysis that one can begin to understand how ordinary people internalize their own sense of national identity, and how they define those categories in relation to others.</etd_ms:description>
        <etd_ms:publisher>Concordia University</etd_ms:publisher>
        <etd_ms:contributor role="advisor">Ingram, Norman</etd_ms:contributor>
        <etd_ms:contributor role="advisor">Penney, Matthew</etd_ms:contributor>
        <etd_ms:date>2025-01</etd_ms:date>
        <etd_ms:type>Electronic Thesis or Dissertation</etd_ms:type>
        <etd_ms:identifier>TC-QMG-995239</etd_ms:identifier>
        <etd_ms:format>text</etd_ms:format>
        <etd_ms:identifier>https://spectrum.library.concordia.ca/id/eprint/995239/1/Hackley_PhD_S2025.pdf</etd_ms:identifier>
        <etd_ms:language>en</etd_ms:language><etd_ms:degree>
        <etd_ms:name>Ph. D.</etd_ms:name>
        <etd_ms:level>phd</etd_ms:level>
        <etd_ms:discipline>History</etd_ms:discipline>
        <etd_ms:grantor>Concordia University</etd_ms:grantor></etd_ms:degree></etd_ms:thesis><etd_ms:thesis xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/ http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/etdms.xsd" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:etd_ms="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/">
        <etd_ms:title>Insights into the roles of novel Epidermal Patterning Factors (EPFs) secreted peptides in stomatal development, and MAP phosphatases MKP2 and DsPTP1 in chloroplast development</etd_ms:title>
        <etd_ms:creator>Kaushik, Pooja</etd_ms:creator>
        <etd_ms:subject/>
        <etd_ms:description>As the global population grows and water scarcity becomes more pressing, improving photosynthetic efficiency and reducing crop losses due to drought stress are critical challenges for modern agriculture. This thesis addresses these challenges by investigating stomatal development, drought stress tolerance, and chloroplast biogenesis in plants. The primary objectives of the research were to identify epidermal patterning factors (EPF) signaling peptides involved in stomatal development in monocot model plant, Brachypodium distachyon (Brachypodium), to explore the role of Arabidopsis thaliana (Arabidopsis) EPFL1, EPFL2, and EPFL3 genes in drought tolerance, and finally, to investigate the roles of Arabidopsis Mitogen Activated Protein Kinase (MAPK) phosphatases (MKP2 and DsPTP1) in chloroplast biogenesis. The findings revealed that Brachypodium EPF peptides (BdEPFL1-1, BdEPFL2-2, BdEPFL6-1, and BdEPFL6-2 play a role in stomatal patterning, with overexpression leading to reduced stomatal density, validated through complementation studies in Arabidopsis. In the drought tolerance study, overexpression of EPFL1 significantly enhanced drought resistance in an ABA-dependent manner, whereas EPFL2 worked in an ABA-independent manner, highlighting distinct regulatory pathways for these gene products. The final part of this research focused on the roles of MAPK phosphatases MKP2 and DsPTP1 in regulating chloroplast biogenesis. Mutant analyses showed that the absence of these phosphatases resulted in impaired chloroplast development, stunted growth, and an albino phenotype, revealing their role as negative regulators of chloroplast formation. Higher order mutants with mutant alleles for MAPKs revealed their likely downstream targets. These findings offer important insights into plant development, with implications for enhancing crop resilience and photosynthesis in response to global climate challenges.</etd_ms:description>
        <etd_ms:publisher>Concordia University</etd_ms:publisher>
        <etd_ms:contributor role="advisor">Gulick, Patrick</etd_ms:contributor>
        <etd_ms:date>2025-02-17</etd_ms:date>
        <etd_ms:type>Electronic Thesis or Dissertation</etd_ms:type>
        <etd_ms:identifier>TC-QMG-995433</etd_ms:identifier>
        <etd_ms:format>text</etd_ms:format>
        <etd_ms:identifier>https://spectrum.library.concordia.ca/id/eprint/995433/1/Kaushik_PhD_W2025.pdf</etd_ms:identifier>
        <etd_ms:language>en</etd_ms:language><etd_ms:degree>
        <etd_ms:name>Ph. D.</etd_ms:name>
        <etd_ms:level>phd</etd_ms:level>
        <etd_ms:discipline>Biology</etd_ms:discipline>
        <etd_ms:grantor>Concordia University</etd_ms:grantor></etd_ms:degree></etd_ms:thesis><etd_ms:thesis xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/ http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/etdms.xsd" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:etd_ms="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/">
        <etd_ms:title>Prediction of In-Plane and Out-of-Plane Defects in Steered Prepreg Tape during Automated Fiber Placement: Experimental and Analytical Modeling</etd_ms:title>
        <etd_ms:creator>Kheradpisheh, Meisam</etd_ms:creator>
        <etd_ms:subject/>
        <etd_ms:description>Automated Fiber Placement (AFP) is a promising technology for manufacturing high-quality, large-scale structural components with complex geometries. However, a major challenge with AFP is the formation of manufacturing-induced defects, such as wrinkles, waviness, and tape folding, that occur during the steering process. These defects arise from the mismatch in length between the inner and outer edges of the prepreg tape when it is placed along a curved path. Such defects can degrade the mechanical properties of the part, leading to a reduction in its quality. Therefore, minimizing or eliminating these defects is crucial to improve the final product's overall quality. This thesis aims to analytically predict the in-plane and out-of-plane defects occurring at a steered tape in the AFP process, and the ultimate goal is to propose some solutions for reducing and eliminating the steering-induced defects. 

A thorough experimental investigation was conducted using a variety of process parameters and steering radii to enhance our understanding of the defect formation during the steering of thermoset prepreg tows. Based on the experimental observations, two micro and macro models were presented to predict planar and non-planar deformations at steered tapes. According to the analytical results, it was then shown that interlayer bonding plays a significant role in the generation of defects in the AFP process. Consequently, a systematic series of experiments and finite element analysis was performed to enhance the interlaminar bondings at the AFP process. At the end according to all experimental and analytical analysis, a novel compaction roller is designed and manufactured to provide variable pressure distributions and contact length based on the geometry of the part, unlike traditional rollers, to reduce and minimize the defect formation during steering.</etd_ms:description>
        <etd_ms:publisher>Concordia University</etd_ms:publisher>
        <etd_ms:contributor role="advisor">Hojjati, Mehdi</etd_ms:contributor>
        <etd_ms:date>2025-03-03</etd_ms:date>
        <etd_ms:type>Electronic Thesis or Dissertation</etd_ms:type>
        <etd_ms:identifier>TC-QMG-995117</etd_ms:identifier>
        <etd_ms:format>text</etd_ms:format>
        <etd_ms:identifier>https://spectrum.library.concordia.ca/id/eprint/995117/1/Kheradpisheh_PhD_W2025.pdf</etd_ms:identifier>
        <etd_ms:language>en</etd_ms:language><etd_ms:degree>
        <etd_ms:name>Ph. D.</etd_ms:name>
        <etd_ms:level>phd</etd_ms:level>
        <etd_ms:discipline>Mechanical Engineering</etd_ms:discipline>
        <etd_ms:grantor>Concordia University</etd_ms:grantor></etd_ms:degree></etd_ms:thesis><etd_ms:thesis xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/ http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/etdms.xsd" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:etd_ms="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/">
        <etd_ms:title>Language Use in Academic Contexts: A Multidimensional Analysis of
Business and Engineering Student Writing</etd_ms:title>
        <etd_ms:creator>Kim, Yoo Lae</etd_ms:creator>
        <etd_ms:subject/>
        <etd_ms:description>This dissertation investigated linguistic variation in student writing across Business and Engineering disciplines through Multidimensional Analysis (MDA). Analyzing a corpus of business case studies and engineering proposals, the study identified five dimensions of variation: Informational Density and Elaborated Discourse, Interactive and Situated Discourse, Narrative Focus, Interpersonal and Dialogic Discourse, and Descriptive and Stative Discourse. These dimensions revealed distinct communicative purposes and rhetorical strategies reflecting disciplinary conventions. Business case studies paid attention to clarity and situational relevance by employing interactive language to engage stakeholders and present actionable solutions. In contrast, Engineering proposals emphasized technical precision and informational density, relying on nominalizations, dense noun phrases, and explicit references to describe systems and processes. Both disciplines also demonstrated shared linguistic features that underline the importance of clarity and coherence. The findings have significant implications for writing pedagogy. Discipline-specific instruction should address the unique linguistic demands of each field while fostering foundational skills transferable across contexts. For Business education, this involves enhancing students’ ability to construct persuasive and audience-aware arguments. Engineering writing instruction should give focus to the technical language and precision. The study further raises questions for future research, including the integration of evolving technologies and the exploration of linguistic variation in interdisciplinary genres. By providing a comprehensive framework for analyzing linguistic variation, this research bridges the gap between academic instruction and professional communication, equipping students to meet the demands of their respective fields.</etd_ms:description>
        <etd_ms:publisher>Concordia University</etd_ms:publisher>
        <etd_ms:contributor role="advisor">McDonough, Kim</etd_ms:contributor>
        <etd_ms:date>2025-02-10</etd_ms:date>
        <etd_ms:type>Electronic Thesis or Dissertation</etd_ms:type>
        <etd_ms:identifier>TC-QMG-995412</etd_ms:identifier>
        <etd_ms:format>text</etd_ms:format>
        <etd_ms:identifier>https://spectrum.library.concordia.ca/id/eprint/995412/1/Kim_PhD_S2025.pdf</etd_ms:identifier>
        <etd_ms:language>en</etd_ms:language><etd_ms:degree>
        <etd_ms:name>Ph. D.</etd_ms:name>
        <etd_ms:level>phd</etd_ms:level>
        <etd_ms:discipline>Applied Linguistics</etd_ms:discipline>
        <etd_ms:grantor>Concordia University</etd_ms:grantor></etd_ms:degree></etd_ms:thesis><etd_ms:thesis xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/ http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/etdms.xsd" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:etd_ms="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/">
        <etd_ms:title>My Mother Always Said, “Don’t Be Lazy With Your Inuktitut: Dismantling Linguistic and Cultural Imperialism in Nunavik.</etd_ms:title>
        <etd_ms:creator>MacDonald, Natasha</etd_ms:creator>
        <etd_ms:subject>decolonization, Inuit, Indigenous research methodology, language preservation, social media</etd_ms:subject>
        <etd_ms:description>In a globalized world where English language and Western culture dominate, Nunavik faces a growing threat of language and cultural loss. This dissertation responds to the urgent need for Inuit-led resistance against colonial pressures by fostering self-determination and cultural resilience in education. Through three interconnected manuscripts, it addresses this need by laying a foundation for decolonizing English second-language (ESL) education in Nunavik. Manuscript A critically examines Nunavik’s colonial history in language education and outlines the importance of Inuit Qaujimajatuqangit as a framework for decolonizing ESL. Manuscript B uncovers gaps in intercultural communication and social media use for protecting Indigenous language and culture, underscoring the lack of Inuit-specific research. These findings inform the empirical study in Manuscript C, which amplifies Inuit voices on how to protect Inuktitut and culture. This dissertation culminates in the development of Silattusarniq, an Inuit-specific methodological framework for research that is grounded in Inuit values and perspectives.</etd_ms:description>
        <etd_ms:publisher>Concordia University</etd_ms:publisher>
        <etd_ms:contributor role="advisor">Corrigan, Julie</etd_ms:contributor>
        <etd_ms:date>2025-02-03</etd_ms:date>
        <etd_ms:type>Electronic Thesis or Dissertation</etd_ms:type>
        <etd_ms:identifier>TC-QMG-995358</etd_ms:identifier>
        <etd_ms:format>text</etd_ms:format>
        <etd_ms:identifier>https://spectrum.library.concordia.ca/id/eprint/995358/1/MacDonald_PhD_S2025.pdf</etd_ms:identifier>
        <etd_ms:language>en</etd_ms:language><etd_ms:degree>
        <etd_ms:name>Ph. D.</etd_ms:name>
        <etd_ms:level>phd</etd_ms:level>
        <etd_ms:discipline>Education</etd_ms:discipline>
        <etd_ms:grantor>Concordia University</etd_ms:grantor></etd_ms:degree></etd_ms:thesis><etd_ms:thesis xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/ http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/etdms.xsd" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:etd_ms="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/">
        <etd_ms:title>Impact Behavior of Hybrid Thermoplastic Composite Laminates and Sandwich Panels</etd_ms:title>
        <etd_ms:creator>Mandegarian, Sepanta</etd_ms:creator>
        <etd_ms:subject/>
        <etd_ms:description>This thesis explores the development, optimization, and impact behavior of hybrid thermoplastic composite laminates and sandwich panels, focusing on environmentally sustainable materials and advanced reinforcement techniques. Double-belt and compression molding lamination methods were optimized to fabricate full thermoplastic composite sandwich panels with 100% recycled PET foam cores. Analyzing the fabrication parameters and final products’ skin-to-core adhesion revealed the critical role of PET foam density and lamination approach in achieving proper bonding. Even though panels made with compression molding outperformed under flexural loads, the continuous nature of the double-belt method offers a reliable and cost-effective alternative production approach.
In the current study, a two-step compression molding method was used to impregnate the metallic mesh layers with PP resin and form a proper connection between the composite layers. Furthermore, the effect of hybridization using stainless-steel mesh layers to reinforce composite laminates and sandwich panels was investigated. Variations of mesh wire size, orientation, and stacking sequence were analyzed to evaluate the energy absorption and damage propagation mechanism of hybrid laminates under different ranges of impact energies. While composite plates show improved performance when the reinforcing metallic layer was positioned at the midplane, it is preferred to reinforce the collision-facing side of sandwich panels for enhanced impact resistance. This strategic placement of the hybrid layer effectively increased the perforation threshold under Low-Velocity Impact (LVI) loading conditions.
In addition, Shape Memory Alloy (SMA) wires were introduced as reinforcing agents of the thermoplastic composite laminates not only to improve the impact performance, but also to take advantage of their specific healing properties to recover the post-impact deformations. Repeated LVI tests demonstrated that the SMA-assisted heating recovery process can restore over 50% of the after-impact deformations, further enhancing the durability and resilience of the composite materials.</etd_ms:description>
        <etd_ms:publisher>Concordia University</etd_ms:publisher>
        <etd_ms:contributor role="advisor">Hojjati, Mehdi</etd_ms:contributor>
        <etd_ms:date>2025-03-04</etd_ms:date>
        <etd_ms:type>Electronic Thesis or Dissertation</etd_ms:type>
        <etd_ms:identifier>TC-QMG-995105</etd_ms:identifier>
        <etd_ms:format>text</etd_ms:format>
        <etd_ms:identifier>https://spectrum.library.concordia.ca/id/eprint/995105/1/Mandegarian_PhD_W2025.pdf</etd_ms:identifier>
        <etd_ms:language>en</etd_ms:language><etd_ms:degree>
        <etd_ms:name>Ph. D.</etd_ms:name>
        <etd_ms:level>phd</etd_ms:level>
        <etd_ms:discipline>Mechanical Engineering</etd_ms:discipline>
        <etd_ms:grantor>Concordia University</etd_ms:grantor></etd_ms:degree></etd_ms:thesis><etd_ms:thesis xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/ http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/etdms.xsd" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:etd_ms="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/">
        <etd_ms:title>Parental Support of Language Development in Multilingual Contexts: Insights from Chinese and Chinese-Canadian Families</etd_ms:title>
        <etd_ms:creator>Mao, Wei</etd_ms:creator>
        <etd_ms:subject>dialogic reading, interactive reading, early bilingualism, immigrant families, parental perspectives</etd_ms:subject>
        <etd_ms:description>This project explores how families living in China and Canada navigate parent-child interactions to support early bilingualism, integrating insights from four interconnected studies. Study 1 examines the perspectives of 16 Chinese parents of 3- to 6-year-olds living in China on two language support strategies: dialogic reading (DR) and co-viewing and conversing about television programs or videos (CVC). Parents recognized these strategies’ potential benefits for language and cognitive development but expressed reservations, including challenges related to child engagement, children’s potential resistance to interruptions, the parent’s own linguistic skills, and the practices’ demands on parental time and effort. These findings underscore the importance of adapting language support strategies to address parents’ practical concerns.
Studies 2, 3 and 4 shift focus to 29 Chinese-Canadian families living in multilingual Montreal, where children were being raised in Mandarin and also regularly exposed to one or more of the local societal languages (French or English). Methods included a parent questionnaire, pretest-posttest observations of storybook reading by parent-child dyads, the use of DR and the digital reading pen by parents and children at home over an eight-week period, and focus group discussions with parents. Study 2 revealed that parents preferred interacting in Mandarin when reading together, even when reading a book written in a societal language. Parents used more dialogic talk, particularly literal questions, with societal language books, but inferential and distancing questions, critical for advanced cognitive and linguistic development, were used sparingly. Study 3 introduced DR instruction to parents, leading to increased use of DR strategies, and thus prompting richer interactions across languages. However, parents reported challenges to DR, such as practical constraints, divergence from home practices, and occasional child resistance. Study 4 introduced a digital reading pen to explore its role in multilingual storybook reading. While the pen eased language demands and promoted child autonomy, it often disrupted parent-child interaction, leading parents to view it as better suited to independent than interactive reading. 
Collectively, the studies bridge gaps between practices recommended in applied research and real-world parenting practices. The findings point to the need for greater collaboration between researchers, parents, and developers of educational tools to develop practices and create resources that align with families’ lived experiences and goals, enriching both research and practice.</etd_ms:description>
        <etd_ms:publisher>Concordia University</etd_ms:publisher>
        <etd_ms:contributor role="advisor">Pesco, Diane</etd_ms:contributor>
        <etd_ms:date>2025-01-29</etd_ms:date>
        <etd_ms:type>Electronic Thesis or Dissertation</etd_ms:type>
        <etd_ms:identifier>TC-QMG-995309</etd_ms:identifier>
        <etd_ms:format>text</etd_ms:format>
        <etd_ms:identifier>https://spectrum.library.concordia.ca/id/eprint/995309/1/Mao_PhD_S2025.pdf</etd_ms:identifier>
        <etd_ms:language>en</etd_ms:language><etd_ms:degree>
        <etd_ms:name>Ph. D.</etd_ms:name>
        <etd_ms:level>phd</etd_ms:level>
        <etd_ms:discipline>Education</etd_ms:discipline>
        <etd_ms:grantor>Concordia University</etd_ms:grantor></etd_ms:degree></etd_ms:thesis><etd_ms:thesis xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/ http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/etdms.xsd" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:etd_ms="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/">
        <etd_ms:title>Interfacial Conformation of Polymer Chains and Its Impact on Film Properties</etd_ms:title>
        <etd_ms:creator>Martins de Lima, Bianca</etd_ms:creator>
        <etd_ms:subject>sum frequency generation spectroscopy
SFG spectroscopy
Polymer conformation
Polymer orientation
interfaces
interfacial conformation
polystyrene
crystallization
thin films
dewetting
fresnel coefficients
optics
non linear optics</etd_ms:subject>
        <etd_ms:description>Polymeric thin films, exhibiting unique optical, electrical, and mechanical properties, can be engineered for various technologies, including adhesives, membranes, optical systems, and electronics. The interfacial region between these films and their environment plays a crucial role in key processes such as nucleation, crystallization, adhesion, and wettability. The conformation of polymer chains near the interface significantly influences these processes. However, there is lack of studies that establish clear correlations between interfacial chain conformation and the macroscopic behavior of thin films. In this study, we employed sum frequency generation (SFG) spectroscopy to investigate the interfacial conformation of polystyrene chains across various systems, establishing valuable relationships between substrate properties, interfacial chain conformation, and macroscopic thin film properties. 
First, we examined the role of the polymer molecular weight in driving interfacial chain conformation. We found significant differences in the conformation of polystyrene chains near a metallic substrate, depending on the polymer molecular weight. Our analysis revealed that the balance between entropy and enthalpy during polymer adsorption plays a crucial role in determining the chain conformation. 
Building on the previous findings, we explored the relationship between the polymer molecular weight, the interfacial environment (free and buried interfaces), the chain conformation and the dewetting behavior of thin films. Our study revealed that polystyrene chains of the same molecular weight adopt distinct conformations depending on the interface and that these differences in chain conformation play a key role in determining the dewetting behavior of thin films. 
Lastly, we conducted a pioneering work demonstrating the potential use of SFG spectroscopy to determine the lamellar orientation at the surface of semi-crystalline thin films. This study broadens the scope of SFG spectroscopy and expands the range of analytical tools available for interfacial lamellar orientation analysis, particularly in complex systems, such as at buried interfaces.
This work provides valuable insights that enhance the fundamental understanding of interfacial properties, chain conformations, and the macroscopic behavior of thin films. By integrating innovative SFG spectroscopy applications with theoretical calculations, we have established a robust foundation for future studies in polymer science and materials engineering, driving advancements in thin film technologies and applications.</etd_ms:description>
        <etd_ms:publisher>Concordia University</etd_ms:publisher>
        <etd_ms:contributor role="advisor">Wood-Adams, Paula</etd_ms:contributor>
        <etd_ms:contributor role="advisor">Hayes, Patrick</etd_ms:contributor>
        <etd_ms:date>2025-01-27</etd_ms:date>
        <etd_ms:type>Electronic Thesis or Dissertation</etd_ms:type>
        <etd_ms:identifier>TC-QMG-995325</etd_ms:identifier>
        <etd_ms:format>text</etd_ms:format>
        <etd_ms:identifier>https://spectrum.library.concordia.ca/id/eprint/995325/1/MartinsdeLima_PhD_S2025.pdf</etd_ms:identifier>
        <etd_ms:language>en</etd_ms:language><etd_ms:degree>
        <etd_ms:name>Ph. D.</etd_ms:name>
        <etd_ms:level>phd</etd_ms:level>
        <etd_ms:discipline>Chemical Engineering</etd_ms:discipline>
        <etd_ms:grantor>Concordia University</etd_ms:grantor></etd_ms:degree></etd_ms:thesis><etd_ms:thesis xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/ http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/etdms.xsd" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:etd_ms="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/">
        <etd_ms:title>Data-Driven Methodology for Model Order Reduction to Predict and Manage Building Energy Flexibility in Smart Grids</etd_ms:title>
        <etd_ms:creator>Maturo, Anthony</etd_ms:creator>
        <etd_ms:subject/>
        <etd_ms:description>The evolving energy landscape, driven by rising demand, electrification, and renewable energy integration, necessitates a shift from traditional “follow-the-load” model to demand-side management. This transition requires accurate prediction of building energy demand, effective demand response participation, and quantification of energy flexibility.
This thesis develops a methodology for predicting and optimizing building thermal energy demand using data from smart thermostats and monitoring infrastructures. Multi-zone buildings and schedule-based operations are modelled using resistance-capacitance (RC) thermal networks. An automated model order reduction approach identifies dominant thermal zones in multi-zone buildings, while control-oriented RC archetypes capture key dynamics in schedule-based operations. Calibration follows a Model Predictive Control Relevant Identification (MRI) process, ensuring models accurately predict thermal dynamics up to 24 hours ahead.
Weather variability is managed through clustering techniques that identify representative days, reducing computational complexity while enabling scenario-driven analysis. This approach bridges the gap between operational and design studies by integrating energy flexibility considerations early in building and community planning.
A distributed economic Model Predictive Control (e-MPC) framework optimizes thermal load management while maintaining occupant comfort and system constraints. It supports applications at both single-building and community scales, such as virtual power plants. Performance is assessed using energy flexibility Key Performance Indicators (efKPIs) against a reference scenario.
The methodology is validated through three case studies: (1) Residential buildings: 30 detached homes equipped with smart thermostats (data from Hydro-Québec); (2) Institutional building: The Varennes Net-Zero Energy Library, Canada’s first net-zero energy institutional building; (3) Community-scale system: A simulated hybrid photovoltaic-battery microgrid in Varennes serving residential and institutional buildings.
Findings highlight how varying building participation in demand response influences aggregated demand profiles, utility metrics (load shifting, peak shaving), and the sizing of grid-supportive technologies. At the single-building level, insights are provided for optimizing thermal load management across convective, radiant, and mixed heating systems. By integrating data-driven modelling, advanced control, and scalable design, this thesis provides actionable solutions for energy efficiency, flexibility, and resilience, supporting a sustainable energy transition.</etd_ms:description>
        <etd_ms:publisher>Concordia University</etd_ms:publisher>
        <etd_ms:contributor role="advisor">Athienitis, Andreas</etd_ms:contributor>
        <etd_ms:contributor role="advisor">Buonomano, Annamaria</etd_ms:contributor>
        <etd_ms:date>2025-01-31</etd_ms:date>
        <etd_ms:type>Electronic Thesis or Dissertation</etd_ms:type>
        <etd_ms:identifier>TC-QMG-995202</etd_ms:identifier>
        <etd_ms:format>text</etd_ms:format>
        <etd_ms:identifier>https://spectrum.library.concordia.ca/id/eprint/995202/1/Maturo_PhD_S2025.pdf</etd_ms:identifier>
        <etd_ms:language>en</etd_ms:language><etd_ms:degree>
        <etd_ms:name>Ph. D.</etd_ms:name>
        <etd_ms:level>phd</etd_ms:level>
        <etd_ms:discipline>Building Engineering</etd_ms:discipline>
        <etd_ms:grantor>Concordia University</etd_ms:grantor></etd_ms:degree></etd_ms:thesis><etd_ms:thesis xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/ http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/etdms.xsd" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:etd_ms="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/">
        <etd_ms:title>Moving the Needle: A Qualitative Evaluation of Implementation Fidelity in Reentry Programming</etd_ms:title>
        <etd_ms:creator>Montgomery, Ashley S.</etd_ms:creator>
        <etd_ms:subject>Program Evaluation; Reentry Program; Violence Prevention Program; Collaborative Evaluation; Community-based; Justice Education;</etd_ms:subject>
        <etd_ms:description>The state of... has notable rates of incarceration and probation combined, with a rate of.. per people. With …residents on probation, the state has systems of confinement within and outside of prison that compare internationally. This state holds a reputation of having the harshest mass punishment laws when it comes to systems of confinement, lead post-offending individuals to pathways back into incarceration. Various research and evaluation studies demonstrate what works when reintegrating groups from prison to community, but there is limited understanding of how reentry programming and its interventions are working and to what degree, beyond quantified success. This study explores the direct experiences of program stakeholders in four facility sites at a reentry program in... Using qualitative evaluation methods to ascertain program fidelity at each of reentry sites, I explore what program recipients and staff members at the program believe affect their environment of a successful transition. Findings implicate the need for additional training in staff members, as well as organizational and inter-organizational dialogue with diverse community member groups that allow for individual-based resource provision and community investment. The data suggests links between paraprofessional staff members’ histories in substance misuse and program participants’ feelings of trust, identity, and safety.</etd_ms:description>
        <etd_ms:publisher>Concordia University</etd_ms:publisher>
        <etd_ms:contributor role="advisor">Waddington, David</etd_ms:contributor>
        <etd_ms:date>2025-02-10</etd_ms:date>
        <etd_ms:type>Electronic Thesis or Dissertation</etd_ms:type>
        <etd_ms:identifier>TC-QMG-995400</etd_ms:identifier>
        <etd_ms:format>text</etd_ms:format>
        <etd_ms:identifier>https://spectrum.library.concordia.ca/id/eprint/995400/1/Montgomery_PhD_S2025.pdf</etd_ms:identifier>
        <etd_ms:language>en</etd_ms:language><etd_ms:degree>
        <etd_ms:name>Ph. D.</etd_ms:name>
        <etd_ms:level>phd</etd_ms:level>
        <etd_ms:discipline>Educational Studies</etd_ms:discipline>
        <etd_ms:grantor>Concordia University</etd_ms:grantor></etd_ms:degree></etd_ms:thesis><etd_ms:thesis xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/ http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/etdms.xsd" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:etd_ms="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/">
        <etd_ms:title>Risk-based Inspection Planning for Reinforced Concrete Bridges</etd_ms:title>
        <etd_ms:creator>Omar, Abdelhady</etd_ms:creator>
        <etd_ms:subject/>
        <etd_ms:description>Bridges are vital components of transportation systems. Bridge decks deteriorate faster than other bridge components due to their direct exposure to traffic loads, harsh environmental conditions, and de-icing chemicals. Inspecting these decks allows for the timely detection of defects, providing data for actionable maintenance decisions, and efficiently allocating resources. Accurate and cost-effective inspection faces many challenges, ranging from standardization of data collection, risk consideration, condition-based inspection frequency, and efficient utilization of Non-destructive Evaluation (NDE) methods.

This research presents an automated, risk-based inspection planning method for reinforced concrete bridges, focusing on bridge decks. This method integrates five main automated modules: (1) a data integration and standardization module, developed to automatically capture, structure, and integrate bridge data from diverse sources, including bridge inspection reports. It also standardizes inspection data into a ready-to-use format that supports direct, subsequent utilization in condition assessment and predictive modeling. It employs web scraping and rule-based data extraction techniques, in addition to text mining, natural language processing, and state-of-the-art large language models. (2) an automated, data-driven condition assessment module, developed to enable quantitative condition assessments of bridge decks using Bayesian belief networks. It makes use of the data generated in the first module. (3) a risk-of-failure module, developed to incorporate both the probability of failure and the consequences of failure, employing advanced ensemble machine learning and deep learning techniques, as well as a fuzzy inference system. (4) an NDE effectiveness module developed to assess the performance of NDE methods based on their respective accuracy, precision, speed, cost, and ease of use. It also evaluates the effectiveness of integrating multiple of these methods to optimize inspection quality and reliability. (5) a dynamic multi-objective optimization module for inspection planning, developed to strike a balance between the structural risk of failure, inspection effectiveness, and inspection costs (both direct costs and impact costs of inspections) under budgetary and operational constraints. This module enables data-driven decision-making to identify which bridges require inspections, the optimal timing for these inspections, and the most effective NDE method for each case.

The developed modules have been tested and validated utilizing inspection data of a set of bridges in Québec, Canada. The data comprises 4,119 bridge structures and 2,255 bridge inspection reports spanning a five-year period from 2018 to 2022. The developed modules demonstrated good performance with significant potential to improve bridge asset management practices. For instance, the defect-based condition assessment module achieved an accuracy of 94.6%, precision of 95.0%, recall of 94.7%, and F1 score of 94.1%. Inspection data was also transformed into a ready-to-use format with an accuracy of 98.79% for detecting and characterizing rebar corrosion, 99.09% for concrete delamination, and 98.64% for cracking, scaling, and spalling of concrete. The developed probability of failure model, as a part of the risk-of-failure module, achieved a mean accuracy of 98.84% with a 0.13% standard deviation. The developed inspection schedules effectively adopted inspection methods based on structural conditions, risk levels, and trade-offs among structural risk of failure, inspection costs, and inspection effectiveness. According to the developed schedules, high-risk bridges should receive more frequent and effective inspections earlier in the planning horizon, while bridges with lower risk need fewer, less intensive inspections. The developed method has the potential to improve inspection effectiveness, reduce costs, rationalize intervention planning (including associated budget and resource allocation), and enable broader, effective utilization of NDE methods.</etd_ms:description>
        <etd_ms:publisher>Concordia University</etd_ms:publisher>
        <etd_ms:contributor role="advisor">Moselhi, Osama</etd_ms:contributor>
        <etd_ms:date>2025-03-05</etd_ms:date>
        <etd_ms:type>Electronic Thesis or Dissertation</etd_ms:type>
        <etd_ms:identifier>TC-QMG-995486</etd_ms:identifier>
        <etd_ms:format>text</etd_ms:format>
        <etd_ms:identifier>https://spectrum.library.concordia.ca/id/eprint/995486/1/Omar_PhD_S2025.pdf</etd_ms:identifier>
        <etd_ms:language>en</etd_ms:language><etd_ms:degree>
        <etd_ms:name>Ph. D.</etd_ms:name>
        <etd_ms:level>phd</etd_ms:level>
        <etd_ms:discipline>Civil Engineering</etd_ms:discipline>
        <etd_ms:grantor>Concordia University</etd_ms:grantor></etd_ms:degree></etd_ms:thesis><etd_ms:thesis xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/ http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/etdms.xsd" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:etd_ms="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/">
        <etd_ms:title>Learning About Internationalization While Learning: Portraying the Discourses of “International Students” Through a Decolonial Lens</etd_ms:title>
        <etd_ms:creator>Ozyonum, Ezgi</etd_ms:creator>
        <etd_ms:subject/>
        <etd_ms:description>This study critically analyzes the transition from aspiring to study abroad to becoming an “international student,” uncovering the colonial structures shaping what is understood as international education. Using a decolonial framework, it shifts the focus from problematizing students to examining the structures and practices of internationalization. Rejecting deficit approaches that emphasize assimilation, it instead interrogates how colonial legacies in international education influence students’ motivations, experiences, and, ultimately, discourses while highlighting their agency in navigating the complexities of studying in Canada.
By employing qualitative methods, specifically critical discourse analysis, this study draws on semi-structured interviews with international engineering master’s students to explore their aspirations, preparations, and the challenges and surprises encountered upon arrival in their host country. The findings reveal the discrepancies between imagined expectations of Canada and lived experiences of international higher education in Quebec, shedding light on the dynamics of “othering” and the colonial structures embedded in international education. Furthermore, the results illuminate patterns of coloniality and emerging practices of decoloniality, providing a deeper understanding of international students’ agency, motivations, and experiences while offering valuable insights to inform future research with international students.</etd_ms:description>
        <etd_ms:publisher>Concordia University</etd_ms:publisher>
        <etd_ms:contributor role="advisor">Tajmel, Tanja</etd_ms:contributor>
        <etd_ms:contributor role="advisor">Carliner, Saul</etd_ms:contributor>
        <etd_ms:date>2025-01-23</etd_ms:date>
        <etd_ms:type>Electronic Thesis or Dissertation</etd_ms:type>
        <etd_ms:identifier>TC-QMG-995457</etd_ms:identifier>
        <etd_ms:format>text</etd_ms:format>
        <etd_ms:identifier>https://spectrum.library.concordia.ca/id/eprint/995457/1/Ozyonum_PhD_S2025.pdf</etd_ms:identifier>
        <etd_ms:language>en</etd_ms:language><etd_ms:degree>
        <etd_ms:name>Ph. D.</etd_ms:name>
        <etd_ms:level>phd</etd_ms:level>
        <etd_ms:discipline>Education</etd_ms:discipline>
        <etd_ms:grantor>Concordia University</etd_ms:grantor></etd_ms:degree></etd_ms:thesis><etd_ms:thesis xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/ http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/etdms.xsd" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:etd_ms="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/">
        <etd_ms:title>Enhancing Hedging Strategies with Deep Reinforcement Learning and Implied Volatility Surfaces</etd_ms:title>
        <etd_ms:creator>Perez Mendoza, Carlos Octavio</etd_ms:creator>
        <etd_ms:subject/>
        <etd_ms:description>This thesis explores the use of deep reinforcement learning (DRL) to enhance dynamic option hedging by incorporating forward-looking market information, mitigating speculation, and optimizing portfolio rebalancing frequency. The first paper, Enhancing Deep Hedging of Options with Implied Volatility Surface Feedback Information, introduces a DRL-based hedging framework that leverages implied volatility surface data, improving hedging performance over traditional methods. The second paper, Is the Difference between Deep Hedging and Delta Hedging a Statistical Arbitrage?, examines whether deep hedging introduces speculative behavior in incomplete markets, demonstrating that proper risk measure selection prevents unwanted speculation. The third paper, Implied-Volatility-Surface-Informed Deep Hedging with Options, extends deep hedging by integrating implied volatility surface-informed decisions, no-trade regions, and multiple hedging instruments, improving cost efficiency and adaptability. This research contributes by defining frameworks that enhance existing techniques for managing risk in financial markets.</etd_ms:description>
        <etd_ms:publisher>Concordia University</etd_ms:publisher>
        <etd_ms:contributor role="advisor">Godin, Frédéric</etd_ms:contributor>
        <etd_ms:date>2025-02-12</etd_ms:date>
        <etd_ms:type>Electronic Thesis or Dissertation</etd_ms:type>
        <etd_ms:identifier>TC-QMG-995347</etd_ms:identifier>
        <etd_ms:format>text</etd_ms:format>
        <etd_ms:identifier>https://spectrum.library.concordia.ca/id/eprint/995347/1/PerezMendoza_PhD_S2025.pdf</etd_ms:identifier>
        <etd_ms:language>en</etd_ms:language><etd_ms:degree>
        <etd_ms:name>Ph. D.</etd_ms:name>
        <etd_ms:level>phd</etd_ms:level>
        <etd_ms:discipline>Mathematics</etd_ms:discipline>
        <etd_ms:grantor>Concordia University</etd_ms:grantor></etd_ms:degree></etd_ms:thesis><etd_ms:thesis xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/ http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/etdms.xsd" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:etd_ms="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/">
        <etd_ms:title>A Methodology for Optimal Load Management and Aggregation Strategies in Grid-Interactive Building Clusters</etd_ms:title>
        <etd_ms:creator>Petrucci, Andrea</etd_ms:creator>
        <etd_ms:subject/>
        <etd_ms:description>The decentralization of energy markets, driven by electrification and renewable energy adoption, necessitates a shift from a “follow-the-supply” to a “follow-the-demand” model, requiring grid operators to digitalize and modernize infrastructure to better accommodate distributed energy production and balance demand. In this context, energy aggregators play a crucial role by enabling building clusters to function as unified entities, thereby optimizing interactions with day-ahead coordination and intra-day markets.
This thesis investigates two key aspects of demand-side management: the role of energy aggregators in shaping residential load profiles and the development of optimal aggregation strategies. These aspects have been scarcely investigated, especially by exploiting measured data. To achieve these goals, a hierarchical control methodology is proposed for energy aggregators to coordinate individual homes within clusters. Leveraging data from smart thermostats and power meters, the methodology integrates predictive modelling and control strategies at a building cluster scale. To this aim, buildings are modelled as reduced-order grey-box networks, capturing thermal dynamics in a simplified yet accurate manner. Machine learning techniques are employed to support the creation of these data-driven models, ensuring robustness and adaptability. Advanced control techniques, such as the economic Model Predictive Control, evaluate energy flexibility by comparing performance to reference demand profiles, ensuring adherence to technical constraints while minimizing the economic expense. A Monte Carlo estimation technique is used to account for variability and heterogeneity within portfolios, facilitating probabilistic decision-making to address uncertainties and diverse operational conditions. Clustering techniques are then used to propose a flexibility-informed benchmarking procedure, supporting the creation of control archetypes and diverse strategies.
The proposed methodology is validated through three case studies and measured dataset of varying populations and resolution: (1) the Experimental House for Building Energetics in Shawinigan, Quebec, a fully instrumented, unoccupied research house to test real implementation of demand-side management; (2) a virtual community of 30 houses in Trois-Rivières, Quebec, equipped with smart thermostats and sensors; and (3) a dataset of approximately 100,000 monitored homes provided by a North American thermostat company enables the creation of energy aggregation strategies and prediction of their aggregated impact on the grid. These case studies demonstrate the effectiveness of energy aggregators in optimizing household costs and support transactive power grid management.
By addressing the dual objectives of cost minimization for customers and operational efficiency for grid operators, this research contributes to the design and implementation of energy aggregators as key enablers of the “follow-the-demand” energy paradigm. This thesis provides actionable insights into energy flexibility and portfolio management, paving the way for the scalable deployment of sustainable and efficient energy systems.</etd_ms:description>
        <etd_ms:publisher>Concordia University</etd_ms:publisher>
        <etd_ms:contributor role="advisor">Athienitis, Andreas K.</etd_ms:contributor>
        <etd_ms:contributor role="advisor">Buonomano, Annamaria</etd_ms:contributor>
        <etd_ms:date>2025-01-29</etd_ms:date>
        <etd_ms:type>Electronic Thesis or Dissertation</etd_ms:type>
        <etd_ms:identifier>TC-QMG-995192</etd_ms:identifier>
        <etd_ms:format>text</etd_ms:format>
        <etd_ms:identifier>https://spectrum.library.concordia.ca/id/eprint/995192/1/Petrucci_PhD_S2025.pdf</etd_ms:identifier>
        <etd_ms:language>en</etd_ms:language><etd_ms:degree>
        <etd_ms:name>Ph. D.</etd_ms:name>
        <etd_ms:level>phd</etd_ms:level>
        <etd_ms:discipline>Building Engineering</etd_ms:discipline>
        <etd_ms:grantor>Concordia University</etd_ms:grantor></etd_ms:degree></etd_ms:thesis><etd_ms:thesis xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/ http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/etdms.xsd" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:etd_ms="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/">
        <etd_ms:title>Impact of Financial Planners, Software, and Specialists on Clients’ Financial Outcomes</etd_ms:title>
        <etd_ms:creator>Pilote, Pierre-Etienne</etd_ms:creator>
        <etd_ms:subject>Financial Advice; Financial Planner; Financial Planning Software; Specialists; Personal Financial Planning; Trust Theory; Agency Theory; Knowledge Concept; Credence Good</etd_ms:subject>
        <etd_ms:description>Personal financial planning (PFP) is a multidisciplinary activity that involves several dimensions and actors including financial institutions, financial advisors, certified financial planners, technology, specialists (e.g., tax, legal) as well as clients. Within two essays, this thesis addresses the following three research questions: 1) What is the impact of the financial advisor on clients’ financial outcomes? 2) How do certified financial planners perceive themselves in the PFP environment? 3) How does the mobilization of two resources, i.e., financial planning software and specialists, by a certified financial planner affects clients’ financial outcomes?

While the evidence suggests that financial advisors have an impact on their clients’ financial outcomes, there is disagreement as to the scope and nature of this impact. Relying on three complementary theoretical lenses (agency theory, trust theory and concept of knowledge) and the six steps of the financial advisory process, the first essay addresses the first research question by proposing a multi-theory model that reconciles findings from previous studies and bridges the gap between research and practice. The model illustrates how the financial advisor impacts each step of the financial advisory process. Furthermore, by being practice-grounded, our model highlights the opacity and complexity of the services offered by the financial advisor and helps to determine whether the advisor’s impact will be positive or negative for their clients.

Addressing the other two research questions, the second essay focuses on certified financial planners and on the resources they can mobilize to serve their clients. Toward that end, we interview 25 certified financial planners. Regarding their self-perception, consistent with existing literature, planners see themselves primarily as generalists. However, we add an important nuance by proposing three different profiles: the true generalist, the generalist focusing on one of the seven PFP areas of expertise, and the generalist focusing on one type of client. These three profiles are represented on a generalist-specialist continuum to illustrate their positioning in relation to the other profiles. As for the PFP software, we show that it features all the characteristics of a decision support system (DSS). Regarding specialists, we again draw on agency theory, trust theory and the concept of knowledge to illustrate, through the six steps of the PFP process, that the involvement of specialists, in-house or external to the financial institution for which the planner works, will have a positive or negative impact on clients’ financial outcomes. Finally, we develop a model explaining how financial planners, the help they receive from resources (PFP software and specialists), and the limited access to these resources imposed by financial institutions, enable or prevent planners from meeting their clients’ needs.</etd_ms:description>
        <etd_ms:publisher>Concordia University</etd_ms:publisher>
        <etd_ms:contributor role="advisor">Boulianne, Emilio</etd_ms:contributor>
        <etd_ms:contributor role="advisor">Magnan, Michel</etd_ms:contributor>
        <etd_ms:date>2025-03-05</etd_ms:date>
        <etd_ms:type>Electronic Thesis or Dissertation</etd_ms:type>
        <etd_ms:identifier>TC-QMG-995454</etd_ms:identifier>
        <etd_ms:format>text</etd_ms:format>
        <etd_ms:identifier>https://spectrum.library.concordia.ca/id/eprint/995454/2/Pilote%20PhD%20F2025.pdf</etd_ms:identifier>
        <etd_ms:language>en</etd_ms:language><etd_ms:degree>
        <etd_ms:name>Ph. D.</etd_ms:name>
        <etd_ms:level>phd</etd_ms:level>
        <etd_ms:discipline>Business Administration (Accountancy specialization)</etd_ms:discipline>
        <etd_ms:grantor>Concordia University</etd_ms:grantor></etd_ms:degree></etd_ms:thesis><etd_ms:thesis xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/ http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/etdms.xsd" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:etd_ms="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/">
        <etd_ms:title>Quilting the Memoir: The Cultural Imaginaries of Egyptian Jewry</etd_ms:title>
        <etd_ms:creator>Rafla, Myriam</etd_ms:creator>
        <etd_ms:subject>research-creation, memory, media, memoir, storytelling, time-based media, Egyptian Jewry</etd_ms:subject>
        <etd_ms:description>Quilting the Memoir: The Cultural Imaginary of Egyptian Jewry engages with three central research issues. First, it explores the role of digital storytelling and memory in articulating the cultural heritage of Egyptian Jewry. Second, it examines the relationships between individual memories, cultural memories, and the cultural imaginary of Egyptian Jewry. Finally, it seeks to understand how personal memoirs and memory objects might find alternative forms of artistic expression in a time-based media installation.
Quilting the Memoir is a research-creation journey that spans a decade, resulting in three separate components – a written dissertation, a WordPress site https://quiltingthememoir.wordpress.com/ and an exhibition of original digital artefacts. Focusing on the mid-20th century exodus of Jews from Egypt and turning to alternative and aesthetic sites of inquiry, this research-creation project aims to generate insight into the ways we remember and represent the past and imagine the future. As a research-creation thesis, Quilting the Memoir demonstrates the value of an engagement with public works, cultural imaginaries and modes of remembering that materialize in alternative research outcomes such as a time-based media installation comprised of digital memory quilts exhibited in a gallery.</etd_ms:description>
        <etd_ms:publisher>Concordia University</etd_ms:publisher>
        <etd_ms:contributor role="advisor">Sawchuk, Kim</etd_ms:contributor>
        <etd_ms:date>2025-03-31</etd_ms:date>
        <etd_ms:type>Electronic Thesis or Dissertation</etd_ms:type>
        <etd_ms:identifier>TC-QMG-995327</etd_ms:identifier>
        <etd_ms:format>text</etd_ms:format>
        <etd_ms:identifier>https://spectrum.library.concordia.ca/id/eprint/995327/1/Rafla_PhD_S2025.pdf</etd_ms:identifier>
        <etd_ms:language>en</etd_ms:language><etd_ms:degree>
        <etd_ms:name>Ph. D.</etd_ms:name>
        <etd_ms:level>phd</etd_ms:level>
        <etd_ms:discipline>Communication</etd_ms:discipline>
        <etd_ms:grantor>Concordia University</etd_ms:grantor></etd_ms:degree></etd_ms:thesis><etd_ms:thesis xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/ http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/etdms.xsd" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:etd_ms="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/">
        <etd_ms:title>Enhancing DeFi by Improving ERC-20 Token Security and Addressing Leveraged Token Shortcomings</etd_ms:title>
        <etd_ms:creator>Rahimian, Mohammadreza</etd_ms:creator>
        <etd_ms:subject/>
        <etd_ms:description>ERC-20 tokens have become widely adopted as tools for representing real-world assets on the blockchain. They function as code, running through smart contracts. However, the development of smart contracts has proven to be error-prone, often leading to security vulnerabilities. This study addresses these issues by systematizing 82 known vulnerabilities and best practices. We then introduce a new ERC-20 implementation, TokenHook, which considers all these security aspects. This improved model outperforms widely used ERC-20 templates in terms of security and reliability.

As the blockchain ecosystem evolves, the rise of leveraged tokens (LVTs) presents additional challenges. They extend the features of ERC-20 by adding decentralized finance (DeFi) functionality. Users can buy and sell LVTs like cryptocurrencies but with amplified returns. However, an analysis of over 1,600 LVTs from 10 issuers reveals critical deficiencies due to the absence of a standardized framework, compromising their return on investment. To protect investors, we introduce LeverEdge, a fully decentralized model designed for deploying LVTs on the blockchain. Unlike existing implementations, LeverEdge operates entirely on-chain, overcoming limitations such as transparency, latency, and gas fees through a hybrid L1-L2 approach. With its security carefully tested, LeverEdge provides a potential reference framework for future decentralized LVT deployments.
 
This progression, from enhancing the security of ERC-20 with TokenHook to developing LeverEdge as a decentralized LVT, contributes to a more secure, transparent, and decentralized approach to DeFi ecosystem.</etd_ms:description>
        <etd_ms:publisher>Concordia University</etd_ms:publisher>
        <etd_ms:contributor role="advisor">Clark, Jeremy</etd_ms:contributor>
        <etd_ms:date>2025-02-13</etd_ms:date>
        <etd_ms:type>Electronic Thesis or Dissertation</etd_ms:type>
        <etd_ms:identifier>TC-QMG-995068</etd_ms:identifier>
        <etd_ms:format>text</etd_ms:format>
        <etd_ms:identifier>https://spectrum.library.concordia.ca/id/eprint/995068/1/Rahimian_PhD_S2025.pdf</etd_ms:identifier>
        <etd_ms:language>en</etd_ms:language><etd_ms:degree>
        <etd_ms:name>Ph. D.</etd_ms:name>
        <etd_ms:level>phd</etd_ms:level>
        <etd_ms:discipline>Information and Systems Engineering</etd_ms:discipline>
        <etd_ms:grantor>Concordia University</etd_ms:grantor></etd_ms:degree></etd_ms:thesis><etd_ms:thesis xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/ http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/etdms.xsd" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:etd_ms="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/">
        <etd_ms:title>Cyber-Physical Resilience Assessment of the Smart Grid</etd_ms:title>
        <etd_ms:creator>Rahiminejad, Abolfazl</etd_ms:creator>
        <etd_ms:subject/>
        <etd_ms:description>Critical National Infrastructure (CNI) provides essential services to society; therefore, any dis-
ruption can have catastrophic consequences for the public and pose significant threats to national
security. Among the various elements of CNI, the power grid serves as the backbone of the en-
ergy infrastructure and holds critical importance, as the functionality of other CNIs heavily depends
on its reliable and secure operation. In this regard, Information and Communication Technologies (ICTs) have been widely integrated into power grids to enable more rigorous monitoring and expedite essential responses to disturbances. This incorporation results in improved service quality, increased reliability, and enhanced resilience. Extensive utilization of ICTs, however, can increase
the risk of cyberattacks against the smart grid. Such attacks can adversely affect the operation of the power delivery system and noticeably degrade its resilience, as evidenced by real-life cyberattacks. To strengthen the resilience of the smart grid against cyberattacks, it is essential to first evaluate its resilience posture. Accordingly, this research aims to develop a quantitative framework for assessing the resilience of the smart grid as a cyber-physical system. The most common resilience paradigm defines resilience through five key phases: preparation, survival, sustainment, recovery, and adaptation. Through this thesis, we provide several innovative solutions across four distinct contributions for assessing the resilience of the smart grid in various phases. In the first contribution, we assess resilience during the preparation phase and explore ways to enhance it. Specifically, we assess the resilience of an islanded microgrid and enhance it through the optimal allocation
of distributed energy resources and diversification of Intelligent Electronic Device (IED) vendors during the design stage. In the operational phase, prior to any cyberattacks, we implement power
system reconfiguration to strengthen preparedness. In the second contribution, we propose a metric for quantifying the resilience of the smart grid during the survival phase within the transmission
domain. This approach is applied to cyberattacks targeting IEC 61850-based substations, focusing on attacks detected in the Industrial Control System (ICS) environment. The proposed solution addresses untrusted data from compromised substations and provides confidence in the results. For the third contribution, we investigate the resilience of substations with a focus on attacks detected in the Regional Control Centre (RCC) environment. We derive three metrics to provide the system’s resilience level, the probability of attack success, and the remaining time before the attack’s final execution. Finally, as the fourth contribution, we introduce a quantitative approach for assessing and enhancing the resilience of the smart grid during the recovery phase within the transmission domain.</etd_ms:description>
        <etd_ms:publisher>Concordia University</etd_ms:publisher>
        <etd_ms:contributor role="advisor">Debbabi, Mourad</etd_ms:contributor>
        <etd_ms:contributor role="advisor">Mohammadi, Arash</etd_ms:contributor>
        <etd_ms:date>2025-02-21</etd_ms:date>
        <etd_ms:type>Electronic Thesis or Dissertation</etd_ms:type>
        <etd_ms:identifier>TC-QMG-995476</etd_ms:identifier>
        <etd_ms:format>text</etd_ms:format>
        <etd_ms:identifier>https://spectrum.library.concordia.ca/id/eprint/995476/1/Rahiminejad_PhD_S2024.pdf</etd_ms:identifier>
        <etd_ms:language>en</etd_ms:language><etd_ms:degree>
        <etd_ms:name>Ph. D.</etd_ms:name>
        <etd_ms:level>phd</etd_ms:level>
        <etd_ms:discipline>Information and Systems Engineering</etd_ms:discipline>
        <etd_ms:grantor>Concordia University</etd_ms:grantor></etd_ms:degree></etd_ms:thesis><etd_ms:thesis xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/ http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/etdms.xsd" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:etd_ms="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/">
        <etd_ms:title>Designing Molybdenum Disulfide Nanocomposite Electrodes for Post-Lithium-Ion Batteries</etd_ms:title>
        <etd_ms:creator>Rahmatinejad, Jalal</etd_ms:creator>
        <etd_ms:subject/>
        <etd_ms:description>Expanding electrical energy storage beyond lithium-ion batteries (LIBs) is crucial due to their limitations in material availability, cost, and performance. LIBs rely on lithium, which has a limited supply, uneven global distribution, and increasing demand, leading to concerns about long-term sustainability and price volatility. Additionally, LIBs face intrinsic challenges such as safety risks from thermal runaway, capacity fading over extended cycles, and performance limitations at extreme temperatures. These constraints drive the search for alternative battery chemistries, such as sodium ion, potassium-ion, magnesium-ion, zincion, and aluminum-ion batteries. However, these alternatives introduce new challenges due to differences in ionic size, charge density, and electrochemical behavior, necessitating the development of advanced electrode materials. Molybdenum disulfide (MoS2), a 2D nanomaterial with larger interlayer spacing than graphene, shows promise for storing such ions but faces challenges from its semiconducting nature and side reactions.
This thesis begins with a comprehensive review of recent literature on strategies for modifying the structure of MoS2 and its nanocomposites to enhance ion storage capabilities for Na+, K+, Mg2+, Zn2+, and Al3+. Next, four novel composites were designed and synthesized, with their potential as active materials for post LIBs comprehensively investigated. A range of material characterization techniques, including Brunauer-Emmett-Teller (BET) surface area analysis, thermogravimetric analysis (TGA), X ray diffraction (XRD), transmission electron microscopy (TEM), and X-ray photoelectron spectroscopy (XPS), were employed to study their structural and chemical properties. To evaluate their electrochemical performance as active battery materials, various methods such as cyclic voltammetry (CV), galvanostatic charge discharge (GCD), and electrochemical impedance spectroscopy (EIS) were utilized. 
Two anode composites for sodium-ion batteries (SIBs), MoS2@HPC (crystalline MoS2 in hierarchically porous carbon) and a-MoSx@HPC (amorphous MoSx in HPC), were designed and evaluated. The hybridization with HPC was found to enhance Na+ storage by improving capacity and cycling stability. At 0.5 A g−1, capacities of 550 mAh g−1 and 301 mAh g−1 were achieved by a-MoSx@HPC and MoS2@HPC, respectively, both outperforming pure MoS2, which delivered 253 mAh g−1. After 100 cycles, capacity retentions of 75% and 89% were maintained by a-MoSx@HPC and MoS2@HPC, respectively, in contrast to the 53% retention observed for pure MoS2.
 Following this, a 1T/2H mixed-phase MoS2 (MP-MoS2) modified with a polyethylene ionomer (I@MP-MoS2) was investigated for Mg2+ storage in magnesium-ion batteries (MIBs) and Mg2+/Li+ storage in dual-salt magnesium-lithium-ion batteries (MLIBs). With 53% of metallic 1T phase, increased interlayer spacing (1.11 nm vs. 0.62 nm in MoS2), and enhanced electrolyte interaction, I@MP-MoS2 achieved 144 mAh g−1 at 20 mA g−1 in MIBs and 270 mAh g−1 in MLIBs, with 87% of capacity retention after 200 cycles.
Finally, a novel cathode design was investigated for MLIBs using a 2D/2D nanocomposite of 1T/2H-MoS2 and delaminated Ti3C2Tx MXene (1T/2H-MoS2@MXene). This structure improves Mg2+ kinetics, structural integrity, and reversible Mg2+/Li+ co-intercalation, achieving 253 mAh g−1 at 50 mA g−1 and retaining 36% of capacity at 1,000 mA g−1.
Overall, this thesis presents innovative MoS2-based materials for post-LIBs, addressing ion storage, conductivity, and stability challenges, contributing to next-generation energy storage solutions.</etd_ms:description>
        <etd_ms:publisher>Concordia University</etd_ms:publisher>
        <etd_ms:contributor role="advisor">Ye, Zhibin</etd_ms:contributor>
        <etd_ms:date>2025-02-11</etd_ms:date>
        <etd_ms:type>Electronic Thesis or Dissertation</etd_ms:type>
        <etd_ms:identifier>TC-QMG-995425</etd_ms:identifier>
        <etd_ms:format>text</etd_ms:format>
        <etd_ms:identifier>https://spectrum.library.concordia.ca/id/eprint/995425/1/Rahmatinejad_PhD_S2025.pdf</etd_ms:identifier>
        <etd_ms:language>en</etd_ms:language><etd_ms:degree>
        <etd_ms:name>Ph. D.</etd_ms:name>
        <etd_ms:level>phd</etd_ms:level>
        <etd_ms:discipline>Chemical Engineering</etd_ms:discipline>
        <etd_ms:grantor>Concordia University</etd_ms:grantor></etd_ms:degree></etd_ms:thesis><etd_ms:thesis xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/ http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/etdms.xsd" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:etd_ms="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/">
        <etd_ms:title>Two Essays on the Role of Reference Point on Consumer Choice Behavior</etd_ms:title>
        <etd_ms:creator>Rayej, Hamzeh</etd_ms:creator>
        <etd_ms:subject/>
        <etd_ms:description>According to the reference point theory, individuals evaluate outcomes based on deviations from a subjective benchmark or expectation. This theory is integral in explaining how unexpected or salient contextual elements reshape consumer attitudes and behaviors. Positive deviations from the reference point are perceived as gains, eliciting favorable emotional and cognitive responses, while negative deviations are seen as losses, often triggering avoidance or corrective actions. In the first essay, reference points emerge from unexpected outcomes of macro-level events, influencing brand exploration through positive mood shifts. In the second essay, the percent daily value (%DV) of added sugars on nutrition labels serves as a reference point that consumers use to evaluate health-related goals. Together, these studies advance understanding of how reference points guide consumer behavior in varied contexts, offering insights into mood dynamics and goal alignment in decision-making.
The first essay focuses on how unexpected macro-level events, like the 2016 U.S. presidential election and the 2018 Super Bowl, influence consumer behavior. These events create reference points when outcomes deviate significantly from expectations. For instance, Trump’s unexpected victory generated strong positive emotional responses among Republican voters, shifting their reference point and leading to increased brand exploratory behavior. Using the Nielsen HomeScan Panel data and a difference-in-differences analysis, the essay reveals that in Republican-leaning counties, the share of new brands in consumer purchases increased by 32.5% post-election, compared to pre-election levels. This shift is attributed to mood elevation stemming from prediction errors, where unexpected positive outcomes encourage novelty-seeking. Similarly, the analysis extends to the 2018 Super Bowl, where the unexpected victory of the Philadelphia Eagles showed comparable effects, reinforcing the generalizability of the findings. This essay bridges reference point theory with real-world behavioral outcomes, providing actionable insights for marketers to leverage mood dynamics during surprise events.
The second essay examines how the inclusion of %DV for added sugars on FDA nutrition labels functions as a salient reference point, influencing consumer attitudes and behaviors. The 100% DV threshold serves as a critical benchmark; products exceeding this value are perceived as inconsistent with health goals, triggering feelings of guilt and reducing purchase intentions. By analyzing store-level sales data and conducting experimental studies, the essay identifies a 2% decline in sales for soft drinks with %DV exceeding 100%, compared to those with lower values. Experiments further reveal that these effects are mediated by consumers’ perceptions of goal inconsistency and anticipated guilt. Reference point theory explains this behavior as consumers compare sugar content to the normative standard set by the 100% DV threshold, framing higher values as losses to their health objectives. This essay not only provides evidence of the practical effectiveness of nutritional labeling but also contributes to understanding the cognitive and emotional mechanisms driving consumer responses to health-related information. These findings have implications for policymakers and marketers seeking to promote healthier choices through effective communication strategies.</etd_ms:description>
        <etd_ms:publisher>Concordia University</etd_ms:publisher>
        <etd_ms:contributor role="advisor">Sobol, Kamila</etd_ms:contributor>
        <etd_ms:contributor role="advisor">SunAh, Kim</etd_ms:contributor>
        <etd_ms:date>2025-01-28</etd_ms:date>
        <etd_ms:type>Electronic Thesis or Dissertation</etd_ms:type>
        <etd_ms:identifier>TC-QMG-995240</etd_ms:identifier>
        <etd_ms:format>text</etd_ms:format>
        <etd_ms:identifier>https://spectrum.library.concordia.ca/id/eprint/995240/1/Rayej_PhD_S2025.pdf</etd_ms:identifier>
        <etd_ms:language>en</etd_ms:language><etd_ms:degree>
        <etd_ms:name>Ph. D.</etd_ms:name>
        <etd_ms:level>phd</etd_ms:level>
        <etd_ms:discipline>Business Administration (Marketing specialization)</etd_ms:discipline>
        <etd_ms:grantor>Concordia University</etd_ms:grantor></etd_ms:degree></etd_ms:thesis><etd_ms:thesis xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/ http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/etdms.xsd" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:etd_ms="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/">
        <etd_ms:title>Don’t Put all your NGOs in the Same Basket: Investigating the Role of NGOs in Implementing Reintegration Policy for Older Adults in Conflict with the Law</etd_ms:title>
        <etd_ms:creator>Revelli, Marina</etd_ms:creator>
        <etd_ms:subject/>
        <etd_ms:description>Western industrialized countries are experiencing an increase in the portion of their populations which are 65 and older. One result of this demographic shift, which is still occurring, is the increasing number of individuals in prisons and jails who are older adults. In Canada, up to 25 % of the federal prison population is considered older. Current studies focus on prison infrastructures and routines which are inadequate for older adults, with many authors suggesting that community placements are more appropriate for this population. Studies on prisoner re-entry focus on the success and use of programs for employment and substance use disorders.
 	This study focuses on an understudied group: older adults under carceral supervision who are provided reintegration services in the community. Grounded in the social construction of target populations framework – alongside NGO research on social constructions, advocacy and resource dependency – this project asks: in a context of the devolution of reintegration policy, what explains how re-entry NGOs act to broaden the bounds of reintegration for older adults? This research uses a four-case comparison of NGOs in Montréal, Toronto, San Francisco and Houston to assess how social constructions of older adults, combined with NGOs’ strategic action through advocacy and resource diversification impacts the bounds of reintegration policy. Newspaper thematic analysis, statistical analysis of funding streams and semi-structured interviews were conducted to compare reintegration services across NGOs. Compared to the two American NGOs, Canadian NGOs provided a greater number and range of services although there was important similarity between the Toronto and San Francisco cases. Within countries the more liberal-leaning cities, with the higher frequency of positive portrayals of aging were associated with more generous bounds of reintegration policy. The findings of this project highlight the importance of considering NGO service providers as agentic rather than passive recipients of correctional department funding. NGOs deploy social constructions, strategic funding searches and advocate to achieve their organizational goals.</etd_ms:description>
        <etd_ms:publisher>Concordia University</etd_ms:publisher>
        <etd_ms:contributor role="advisor">Marier, Patrik</etd_ms:contributor>
        <etd_ms:date>2025-01-31</etd_ms:date>
        <etd_ms:type>Electronic Thesis or Dissertation</etd_ms:type>
        <etd_ms:identifier>TC-QMG-995441</etd_ms:identifier>
        <etd_ms:format>text</etd_ms:format>
        <etd_ms:identifier>https://spectrum.library.concordia.ca/id/eprint/995441/1/Revelli_PhD_S2025.pdf</etd_ms:identifier>
        <etd_ms:language>en</etd_ms:language><etd_ms:degree>
        <etd_ms:name>Ph. D.</etd_ms:name>
        <etd_ms:level>phd</etd_ms:level>
        <etd_ms:discipline>Political Science</etd_ms:discipline>
        <etd_ms:grantor>Concordia University</etd_ms:grantor></etd_ms:degree></etd_ms:thesis><etd_ms:thesis xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/ http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/etdms.xsd" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:etd_ms="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/">
        <etd_ms:title>The Effect of Therapeutic Exercises on Paraspinal Muscle Morphology and Function in Chronic Low Back Pain</etd_ms:title>
        <etd_ms:creator>Rosenstein, Brent</etd_ms:creator>
        <etd_ms:subject>low back pain, exercise therapy, paraspinal muscle, MRI, function, quality of life, patient-reported outcome measures</etd_ms:subject>
        <etd_ms:description>Low back pain (LBP) is the most common musculoskeletal disorder globally, and a leading cause of disability, especially when it becomes chronic. Exercise therapy is the most widely used form of conservative treatment for chronic LBP. Due to the link between changes in paraspinal muscle morphology (e.g. atrophy, fatty infiltration) and LBP, many exercise interventions focus on activating paraspinal muscles. Past findings suggest the benefits of exercise for individuals with chronic LBP on patient-reported outcomes, including improvements in pain, disability and quality of life. However, the best type of exercise to improve paraspinal muscle health in chronic LBP is understudied, and therefore, remains unclear. This 7-chapter dissertation aims to use magnetic resonance imaging to comprehensively investigate the effect of different exercise programs on paraspinal muscle morphology and function, and its association with patient-reported outcomes in individuals with chronic LBP. Chapter 1 explains the rationale, objectives, and hypotheses, and Chapter 2 consists of a comprehensive review of the literature. Chapter 3 explains an aquatic therapy protocol. Chapter 4 aimed to investigate the effect of an aquatic therapy program versus standard care on paraspinal muscle morphology and function, and the association of morphological changes with strength and patient-reported outcomes. Similarly, Chapter 5 aimed to investigate the effect of a combined motor control and isolated lumbar extension strengthening program versus general exercise on paraspinal muscle morphology and psychosocial factors, and the association of morphological changes with strength and patient-reported outcomes. Finally, Chapter 6 aimed to investigate the effect of a multimodal exercise program versus no exercise on paraspinal muscle morphology and patient-reported outcomes, and the association of morphological changes with patient-reported outcomes and functional outcomes. Lastly, Chapter 7 summarizes the results of Chapter 4-6 and states the general limitations, recommendations for future research, and conclusions.</etd_ms:description>
        <etd_ms:publisher>Concordia University</etd_ms:publisher>
        <etd_ms:contributor role="advisor">Fortin, Maryse</etd_ms:contributor>
        <etd_ms:date>2025-02-05</etd_ms:date>
        <etd_ms:type>Electronic Thesis or Dissertation</etd_ms:type>
        <etd_ms:identifier>TC-QMG-995278</etd_ms:identifier>
        <etd_ms:format>text</etd_ms:format>
        <etd_ms:identifier>https://spectrum.library.concordia.ca/id/eprint/995278/1/Rosenstein_PhD_S2025.pdf</etd_ms:identifier>
        <etd_ms:language>en</etd_ms:language><etd_ms:degree>
        <etd_ms:name>Ph. D.</etd_ms:name>
        <etd_ms:level>phd</etd_ms:level>
        <etd_ms:discipline>Health and Exercise Science</etd_ms:discipline>
        <etd_ms:grantor>Concordia University</etd_ms:grantor></etd_ms:degree></etd_ms:thesis><etd_ms:thesis xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/ http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/etdms.xsd" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:etd_ms="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/">
        <etd_ms:title>Investigating Surrogate-based Models for Holistic Building Performance Assessment and Retrofit Solutions</etd_ms:title>
        <etd_ms:creator>Saad, Mostafa</etd_ms:creator>
        <etd_ms:subject/>
        <etd_ms:description>Existing commercial buildings in Québec are responsible for a major share of GHG emissions within the local building sector, yet limited progress has been achieved in their operational transformations over the past decades. Building retrofit is recognized as a key approach to improving energy efficiency while considering the intertwining economic and environmental effects of the applied retrofit measures. Balancing these objectives transforms the problem into a high-dimensional, multi-objective, and challenging task requiring iterative simulations. When conventional physics-based approaches are used, such analyses become computationally prohibitive, with the challenge further intensifying when analyzing multiple buildings or extending the scope to future building performance.
This thesis addresses the highlighted challenge by developing surrogate models that allow the investigation of high-dimensional retrofit analyses. The study establishes a holistic building retrofit framework for post-industrialized buildings within the Montréal region to rigorously identify feasible retrofit measures specific to the studied building typology. It further develops robust surrogate models for energy consumption, embodied carbon, and investment costs that aid in decision-making across a wide array of measures. The methodology is further extended to integrate future building performance through feature extraction methods. Similarly, the study extends the generalizability of the surrogates to a multi-building analysis using a bottom-up approach, which integrates additional training data samples. Given the prevalence of data scarcity in commercial buildings, the methodology integrates building archetypes while identifying the modelling approach that accurately represents the studied building typology. 
The findings demonstrate the robustness of the surrogate-based approach in building retrofit analyses, highlighting a significant improvement in computational efficiency. This thesis introduces a comprehensive methodological framework that advances building performance assessment using surrogate-based methods, identifying their limitations and effectiveness in the building retrofit research domain.</etd_ms:description>
        <etd_ms:publisher>Concordia University</etd_ms:publisher>
        <etd_ms:contributor role="advisor">Eicker, Ursula</etd_ms:contributor>
        <etd_ms:date>2025-03-05</etd_ms:date>
        <etd_ms:type>Electronic Thesis or Dissertation</etd_ms:type>
        <etd_ms:identifier>TC-QMG-995464</etd_ms:identifier>
        <etd_ms:format>text</etd_ms:format>
        <etd_ms:identifier>https://spectrum.library.concordia.ca/id/eprint/995464/1/Saad_PhD_S2025.pdf</etd_ms:identifier>
        <etd_ms:language>en</etd_ms:language><etd_ms:degree>
        <etd_ms:name>Ph. D.</etd_ms:name>
        <etd_ms:level>phd</etd_ms:level>
        <etd_ms:discipline>Building Engineering</etd_ms:discipline>
        <etd_ms:grantor>Concordia University</etd_ms:grantor></etd_ms:degree></etd_ms:thesis><etd_ms:thesis xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/ http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/etdms.xsd" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:etd_ms="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/">
        <etd_ms:title>Techniques to Improve the Parsing of Unstructured Logs for AIOps</etd_ms:title>
        <etd_ms:creator>Sedki, Issam</etd_ms:creator>
        <etd_ms:subject/>
        <etd_ms:description>Artificial Intelligence for IT Operations (AIOps) is revolutionizing IT management by incorporating AI, machine learning, and big data analytics to automate and enhance system operations. Logs are the backbone of AIOps—they provide the fundamental data on system events, user activities, and performance metrics that AIOps needs for proactive monitoring, predictive analytics, and maintaining system health. Log management, especially log parsing, is therefore critical for identifying anomalies, diagnosing failures, and ensuring overall operational efficiency. However, challenges such as diverse log formats, insufficient logging guidelines, the sheer volume of logs, and the need for real-time insights significantly limit the precision, scalability, and effectiveness of AIOps.
This thesis develops novel methods for universal log parsing, introduces accurate evaluation metrics, proposes a comprehensive taxonomy of log characteristics, and addresses privacy compliance, collectively advancing the efficacy, scalability, and trustworthiness of AIOps.
Inaccurate log parsing can lead to inaccurate insights—misleading or incorrect conclusions drawn from analysis. Such errors may cause AIOps to misclassify events, overlook crucial anomalies, or generate noise that obscures genuine issues. To address this, the first major contribution of this thesis is the development of ULP (Universal Log Parser), which leverages a frequent token counting method to identify recurring patterns and extract log templates efficiently. By reducing computational complexity, ULP enables faster, more accurate log parsing, making it highly effective for large-scale IT environments—a key capability for the automation and responsiveness required in AIOps.
The second contribution is AML (Accuracy Metric for Log Parsing), a structured framework for evaluating the accuracy of log parsing. Traditional metrics are insufficient for heterogeneous log formats, leading to errors and subsequent misguided AIOps decisions. AML offers nuanced metrics that account for both omission and commission errors, enabling detailed and reliable comparisons across different log parsers.
The third contribution is a taxonomy of log characteristics, categorizing logs based on their structural and contextual properties. This taxonomy not only guides parser design by clarifying how logs differ across applications but also informs logging practices, helping practitioners tailor log writing strategies for better analytics.
The fourth contribution focuses on enhancing log privacy compliance, a crucial aspect in AIOps —especially as automated processes handle large volumes of sensitive log data. The thesis provides guidelines for evaluating and managing privacy risks associated with log data, ensuring that the automation capabilities of AIOps remain compliant with stringent privacy regulations and best practices.
Together, these contributions form a framework for advancing log parsing within AIOps. It is a holistic approach—encompassing efficient universal parsing, robust accuracy evaluation, a guiding taxonomy, and built-in privacy compliance—that addresses the entire life cycle of log-based analytics. This framework ultimately strengthens the capabilities of IT operations to be more proactive, responsive, and compliant, paving the way for the next generation of AIOps-driven IT management.</etd_ms:description>
        <etd_ms:publisher>Concordia University</etd_ms:publisher>
        <etd_ms:contributor role="advisor">Hamou-Lhadj, Abdelwahab</etd_ms:contributor>
        <etd_ms:contributor role="advisor">Ait Mohamed, Otmane</etd_ms:contributor>
        <etd_ms:date>2025-03-27</etd_ms:date>
        <etd_ms:type>Electronic Thesis or Dissertation</etd_ms:type>
        <etd_ms:identifier>TC-QMG-995238</etd_ms:identifier>
        <etd_ms:format>text</etd_ms:format>
        <etd_ms:identifier>https://spectrum.library.concordia.ca/id/eprint/995238/1/Sedki_PhD_S2025.pdf</etd_ms:identifier>
        <etd_ms:language>en</etd_ms:language><etd_ms:degree>
        <etd_ms:name>Ph. D.</etd_ms:name>
        <etd_ms:level>phd</etd_ms:level>
        <etd_ms:discipline>Electrical and Computer Engineering</etd_ms:discipline>
        <etd_ms:grantor>Concordia University</etd_ms:grantor></etd_ms:degree></etd_ms:thesis><etd_ms:thesis xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/ http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/etdms.xsd" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:etd_ms="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/">
        <etd_ms:title>Development of Computation-Efficient Computer Vision Systems for High-Quality Brain Tumor Segmentation</etd_ms:title>
        <etd_ms:creator>Sun, Yanming</etd_ms:creator>
        <etd_ms:subject/>
        <etd_ms:description>In this thesis, two design methodologies are proposed, and also applied in the development of 2 computer-vision systems for computation-efficient and high-quality brain-tumor detection.

The first methodology aims at developing systems to detect, by conventional image processing procedures, 3D-object locations with a pixel-wise precision. The main operations of the detection are predicting gray-level distribution of the pixels in the object region and, based the prediction result, identifying/removing regions of non-interest. As 3D inputs can be sliced into axial, coronal or sagittal slice series, the prediction/identification/removal operations are performed step-by-step to the 3 series, respectively. Each removal increases the density of the object-information, facilitating the next prediction. To comprehend the pixel distributions with their locations, a 2D histogram presentation is proposed. In the design of the brain-tumor detection system, it is used to highlight the left-right asymmetry of a brain structure. Since the asymmetry is caused by tumors and non-pathological elements, an adaptive histogram modulation method is proposed to enhance the former by attenuating the latter. The prediction/identification/removal operations transform a 3D brain image into a tumoral minimum bounding box, which is then transformed into a tumor mask using simple morphological operations. The test results, on 1251 samples, have confirmed the high quality of the prediction of the tumor data distributions and the tumor detection.

The second methodology is proposed to design CNN (convolutional neural network) systems handling a complex task of brain-tumor segmentation, i.e., classifying the pixels of a brain image into 4 classes of intra-tumoral regions and the background. The methodology is to decompose this complex task into simple subtasks and each of them is performed by a simply-configurated and independently-trained CNN. By doing so, one can optimize the use of computing power and minimize the gradient conflict in training. The 4-class classification is decomposed into 3 binary classifications. Each of them is further decomposed into 2: first locating the object region and then identifying the pixels inside the region, performed by 2 independent-and-simple modules. The overall system, requiring only 0.75M trainable parameters, has been trained/tested with BraTS datasets, and its processing quality is among the best reported recently.</etd_ms:description>
        <etd_ms:publisher>Concordia University</etd_ms:publisher>
        <etd_ms:contributor role="advisor">Wang, Chunyan</etd_ms:contributor>
        <etd_ms:date>2025-03-11</etd_ms:date>
        <etd_ms:type>Electronic Thesis or Dissertation</etd_ms:type>
        <etd_ms:identifier>TC-QMG-995488</etd_ms:identifier>
        <etd_ms:format>text</etd_ms:format>
        <etd_ms:identifier>https://spectrum.library.concordia.ca/id/eprint/995488/1/Sun_PhD_S2025.pdf</etd_ms:identifier>
        <etd_ms:language>en</etd_ms:language><etd_ms:degree>
        <etd_ms:name>Ph. D.</etd_ms:name>
        <etd_ms:level>phd</etd_ms:level>
        <etd_ms:discipline>Electrical and Computer Engineering</etd_ms:discipline>
        <etd_ms:grantor>Concordia University</etd_ms:grantor></etd_ms:degree></etd_ms:thesis><etd_ms:thesis xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/ http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/etdms.xsd" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:etd_ms="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/">
        <etd_ms:title>Cryptocurrency’s Societal Impact: ESG Compliance, Gaming Economies, and Political Finance</etd_ms:title>
        <etd_ms:creator>Sévigny, Stéphane</etd_ms:creator>
        <etd_ms:subject/>
        <etd_ms:description>This dissertation investigates the transformative role of cryptocurrency across three critical domains: environmental, social, and governance (ESG) compliance, blockchain-integrated gaming (GameFi), and political finance (PolitiFi). Through a thesis-by-article structure, it presents three complementary studies that together explore cryptocurrency’s broader societal impact and its implications for innovation in finance and governance.
The first article critically evaluates Bitcoin’s alignment with ESG criteria, challenging the dominant narrative that emphasizes its environmental footprint. Utilizing a novel forecast model, the study projects Bitcoin’s energy consumption and highlights overlooked contributions to financial inclusion, renewable energy integration, and governance transparency. This work offers insights into how Bitcoin’s environmental criticisms may be mitigated through technological advancements and innovative mining practices.
The second article examines the emerging GameFi sector, which bridges decentralized finance (DeFi), non-fungible tokens (NFTs), and gaming. By analyzing key developments such as play-to-earn models and blockchain gaming’s evolution, the study uses empirical methods to explore GameFi’s independence from traditional cryptocurrency markets. It reveals how GameFi redefines digital economies, providing new monetization opportunities and reshaping value exchange between players and developers.
The third article introduces PolitiFi, a novel category of cryptocurrencies linked to political campaigns and figures. Employing a Vector Autoregressive (VAR) model, the study investigates PolitiFi’s market dynamics and its rapid decoupling from traditional meme coins. It demonstrates PolitiFi’s potential to engage underrepresented voters, influence campaign strategies, and disrupt traditional political finance.
Together, these studies provide a cohesive examination of cryptocurrency’s societal contributions, addressing critical challenges and uncovering opportunities for its application in diverse fields. The findings contribute to academic discourse on decentralized technologies while offering practical implications for policy-making, sustainable finance, and digital innovation.</etd_ms:description>
        <etd_ms:publisher>Concordia University</etd_ms:publisher>
        <etd_ms:contributor role="advisor">Schweizer, Denis</etd_ms:contributor>
        <etd_ms:contributor role="advisor">Proelss, Juliane</etd_ms:contributor>
        <etd_ms:date>2025-02-14</etd_ms:date>
        <etd_ms:type>Electronic Thesis or Dissertation</etd_ms:type>
        <etd_ms:identifier>TC-QMG-995333</etd_ms:identifier>
        <etd_ms:format>text</etd_ms:format>
        <etd_ms:identifier>https://spectrum.library.concordia.ca/id/eprint/995333/1/S%C3%A9vigny_PhD_S2025.pdf</etd_ms:identifier>
        <etd_ms:language>en</etd_ms:language><etd_ms:degree>
        <etd_ms:name>Ph. D.</etd_ms:name>
        <etd_ms:level>phd</etd_ms:level>
        <etd_ms:discipline>Business Administration (Finance specialization)</etd_ms:discipline>
        <etd_ms:grantor>Concordia University</etd_ms:grantor></etd_ms:degree></etd_ms:thesis><etd_ms:thesis xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/ http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/etdms.xsd" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:etd_ms="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/">
        <etd_ms:title>The Real Friends Are The Machines We Made Along The Way</etd_ms:title>
        <etd_ms:creator>Thibodeau, Joseph</etd_ms:creator>
        <etd_ms:subject/>
        <etd_ms:description>Machine-human relationships exemplify humanity’s relationships with materiality at-large, as well as relationships with the "other", with society, and with the notion of “human” itself. This thesis investigates the social construction of ontological boundaries between humans and machines through a research-creation process centred around technician-machine relationships in design, maintenance and repair. Over the course of six years, the author developed four major projects that serve as case studies, each focused on a specific kind of social encounter: Machine Ménagerie, an installation and research-performance around relationships in design; Chronogenica, a machine-human cooperative organization; Ritualizing Care in Human-Robot Relations, an artistic residency with a robot collaborator; and The Nature Reserve of Useless Robots, an interactive installation for showing care towards machines.

Drawing on the knowledge-sharing practices of technician communities, the author uses narrative as a primary method for conveying the idiosyncrasies of each project and the specific machines involved. In return for the author’s care and attention, and given space to express themselves on their own terms, the machines contributed something of their own knowledge to the thesis. Supposedly-objective dominant truths about machine-ness fell away to reveal an underlying irrationality, highlighting the everyday practices of reality-construction that can empower us to alter our relationships with those nonhumans we care for (and who care for us).</etd_ms:description>
        <etd_ms:publisher>Concordia University</etd_ms:publisher>
        <etd_ms:contributor role="advisor">Howes, David</etd_ms:contributor>
        <etd_ms:contributor role="advisor">Jarry, Alice</etd_ms:contributor>
        <etd_ms:contributor role="advisor">Montanaro, Michael</etd_ms:contributor>
        <etd_ms:contributor role="advisor">Penhune, Virginia</etd_ms:contributor>
        <etd_ms:date>2025-01-28</etd_ms:date>
        <etd_ms:type>Electronic Thesis or Dissertation</etd_ms:type>
        <etd_ms:identifier>TC-QMG-995285</etd_ms:identifier>
        <etd_ms:format>text</etd_ms:format>
        <etd_ms:identifier>https://spectrum.library.concordia.ca/id/eprint/995285/1/Thibodeau_PhD_S2025.pdf</etd_ms:identifier>
        <etd_ms:language>en</etd_ms:language><etd_ms:degree>
        <etd_ms:name>Ph. D.</etd_ms:name>
        <etd_ms:level>phd</etd_ms:level>
        <etd_ms:discipline>Individualized Program</etd_ms:discipline>
        <etd_ms:grantor>Concordia University</etd_ms:grantor></etd_ms:degree></etd_ms:thesis><etd_ms:thesis xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/ http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/etdms.xsd" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:etd_ms="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/">
        <etd_ms:title>Automation And Intelligence In IT Operation Management: Machine Learning for Capacity Planning and Load Testing Optimization</etd_ms:title>
        <etd_ms:creator>Vitui, Arthur Marius</etd_ms:creator>
        <etd_ms:subject/>
        <etd_ms:description>The increasing complexity and scale of modern IT infrastructures necessitate innovative strategies to maintain efficiency, reliability, and cost effectiveness. Large scale industrial systems require precise capacity planning to manage fluctuating demands, prevent downtime, and operate within optimal cost parameters. However, traditional capacity planning methods often fall short in today’s dynamic environments. This dissertation introduces an agentic approach to AIOps (Artificial Intelligence for IT Operations) aimed at enhancing the maintenance and operational stability of large scale systems. Effective capacity planning is essential for stable system operations. Over provisioning leads to resource waste, while under provisioning can cause failures and diminished performance. By utilizing load testing data and advanced machine learning (ML) models, we propose a blueprint process that optimizes system capacity planning. Integrating ML into this process enhances predictive capabilities, enabling proactive resource scaling, reducing costs, and increasing system resilience. A significant challenge in optimizing this process is the inefficiency and time consuming nature of traditional load testing. Existing methodologies often require substantial manual effort and considerable time to simulate large scale workloads. To address this, we propose a framework that streamlines load testing through automation and early stopping rules based on spike detection techniques for system Key Performance Indicators (KPIs). By leveraging a system’s ability to predict KPI spikes, we can dynamically adjust capacity as needed. We aim to integrate these processes into tools utilized by LLM (Large Language Model) agents within an AIOps system. These tools will act as intermediaries for monitoring and maintaining large scale systems. This integration will establish a fully managed architecture, where AIOps agents enhance the IT operations team’s ability to perform proactive maintenance, respond to new incidents, autonomously monitor system health, predict potential issues, and implement proactive measures to maintain optimal performance. This dissertation presents a novel approach to enhancing efficiency in large scale systems by combining automation and load testing improvements with machine learning and LLM agents. By developing a comprehensive, scalable framework, this research seeks to reduce operational overhead and establish a new standard for IT system management and load testing practices within the Software Development Life Cycle (SDLC) in industrial settings.</etd_ms:description>
        <etd_ms:publisher>Concordia University</etd_ms:publisher>
        <etd_ms:contributor role="advisor">Chen, Tse-Hsun</etd_ms:contributor>
        <etd_ms:date>2025-02-27</etd_ms:date>
        <etd_ms:type>Electronic Thesis or Dissertation</etd_ms:type>
        <etd_ms:identifier>TC-QMG-995480</etd_ms:identifier>
        <etd_ms:format>text</etd_ms:format>
        <etd_ms:identifier>https://spectrum.library.concordia.ca/id/eprint/995480/1/Vitui_PhD_S2025.pdf</etd_ms:identifier>
        <etd_ms:language>en</etd_ms:language><etd_ms:degree>
        <etd_ms:name>Ph. D.</etd_ms:name>
        <etd_ms:level>phd</etd_ms:level>
        <etd_ms:discipline>Computer Science</etd_ms:discipline>
        <etd_ms:grantor>Concordia University</etd_ms:grantor></etd_ms:degree></etd_ms:thesis><etd_ms:thesis xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/ http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/etdms.xsd" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:etd_ms="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/">
        <etd_ms:title>Intelligent Anomaly Detection for 5G &amp; Beyond: Securing
Service-Based Architecture Against HTTP/2-Driven Attacks</etd_ms:title>
        <etd_ms:creator>Wehbe, Nathalie</etd_ms:creator>
        <etd_ms:subject>5G networks, 5G security, HTTP/2, HTTP/2 attacks, 5G SBA security, 5G dataset, machine learning, anomaly detection, time series transformer, ensemble learning, application-layer features</etd_ms:subject>
        <etd_ms:description>The Fifth Generation (5G) networks power diverse applications, from autonomous vehicles to smart cities, by enabling ultra-reliable low-latency communications, massive IoT connectivity, and enhanced mobile broadband. At the core of this advancement is the 5G Service-Based Architecture (SBA), which ensures scalability and flexibility through cloud-native deployment and virtualized Network Functions (NFs). The adoption of the Hypertext Transfer Protocol version 2 (HTTP/2) in the 5G SBA has become essential for enabling efficient communication between NFs. However, the adoption of HTTP/2 for NF communication introduces security risks, including stream multiplexing, slow-rate, and rapid-reset attacks, which can lead to Denial of Service (DoS) and disrupt critical services. Addressing these vulnerabilities is essential to maintaining the stability and security of 5G networks. 
This thesis explores the impact of HTTP/2 vulnerabilities on the 5G SBA, identifying attack vectors that compromise the Quality of Service (QoS) of critical services. While prior studies largely assessed these threats theoretically, this research demonstrates the practical vulnerabilities of 5G networks to HTTP/2 attacks, such as Stream Multiplexing Attacks (SMAs). To address these challenges, the thesis introduces 5GShield, an application layer anomaly detection solution using autoencoder-based Machine Learning (ML). By profiling normal NF behavior with application-layer features, 5GShield effectively detects deviations indicative of SMAs. Building on this, 5GGuardian is proposed as a more advanced solution to detect nuanced variations of SMAs. Leveraging 5G-Stream features and a time-series transformer, 5GGuardian captures fine-grained NF behaviors and complex patterns in HTTP/2 streams, achieving superior accuracy for both stealthy and non-stealthy anomalies. Recognizing the limitations of single detection approaches, the research introduces an ensemble learning-based solution that leverages and combines the strengths of multiple ML models trained on different feature sets in order to provide superior detection performance of HTTP/2 attacks, including slow-rate and rapid-reset attacks. By providing scalable and advanced anomaly detection, this thesis strengthens 5G SBA security, ensuring reliable service delivery and supporting the secure growth of future communication networks.</etd_ms:description>
        <etd_ms:publisher>Concordia University</etd_ms:publisher>
        <etd_ms:contributor role="advisor">Assi, Chadi</etd_ms:contributor>
        <etd_ms:contributor role="advisor">Assem Alameddine, Hyame</etd_ms:contributor>
        <etd_ms:date>2025-02-03</etd_ms:date>
        <etd_ms:type>Electronic Thesis or Dissertation</etd_ms:type>
        <etd_ms:identifier>TC-QMG-995162</etd_ms:identifier>
        <etd_ms:format>text</etd_ms:format>
        <etd_ms:identifier>https://spectrum.library.concordia.ca/id/eprint/995162/6/Wehbe_PhD_S2025.pdf</etd_ms:identifier>
        <etd_ms:language>en</etd_ms:language><etd_ms:degree>
        <etd_ms:name>Ph. D.</etd_ms:name>
        <etd_ms:level>phd</etd_ms:level>
        <etd_ms:discipline>Information and Systems Engineering</etd_ms:discipline>
        <etd_ms:grantor>Concordia University</etd_ms:grantor></etd_ms:degree></etd_ms:thesis><etd_ms:thesis xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/ http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/etdms.xsd" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:etd_ms="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/">
        <etd_ms:title>Nonreciprocal Vibration Transmission in Discrete Periodic Systems with Spatiotemporal Modulations</etd_ms:title>
        <etd_ms:creator>Wu, Jiuda</etd_ms:creator>
        <etd_ms:subject/>
        <etd_ms:description>Materials with time-varying properties enable direction-dependent vibration transmission, meaning that interchanging the source and receiver changes transmission characteristics such as amplitude, phase, or wave speed, resulting in nonreciprocal behaviour. While unidirectional transmission in long, weakly modulated systems has been widely studied, the transmission characteristics of short, strongly modulated systems remain underexplored. This thesis addresses this gap, aiming to expand the application of materials and devices with time-varying mechanical properties. The focus is on discrete models of spatiotemporally modulated systems, where effective elasticity changes harmonically in time and space. 
A methodology is developed to accurately predict the steady-state response of spatiotemporally modulated systems in response to external harmonic drive. The formulation is valid for strongly modulated systems of an arbitrary number of units. Using this methodology, vibration transmission characteristics of both weakly and strongly modulated systems are investigated. Contributions of primary and sideband resonances, and their overlaps, to nonreciprocity are clarified. The effects of modulation amplitude and wavenumber on the resonance frequencies are discussed. 
The contribution of phase to nonreciprocity is highlighted, a feature that is often overlooked in the literature. It is shown that the difference between the transmitted phases is the primary contributor to nonreciprocity in short systems. To further emphasize the significant role of phase, a nonreciprocal response regime is introduced which is characterized by equal transmitted amplitudes in opposite directions. A nonreciprocal phase shift is the sole contributor to nonreciprocity in this case. A methodology is developed for achieving nonreciprocal phase shifts in short, weakly modulated systems based on the envelope of the response. A formulation is also presented that ensures the shapes of the transmitted response envelopes have the same shape but different phases. 
Parametric stability is analyzed using Floquet theory, revealing the influence of key system parameters, including modulation phase, wavenumber, amplitude, frequency, damping, and system size. Perturbation theory shows that parametric instability occurs at specific frequency combinations of the unmodulated system. Instability is more likely at higher modulation frequencies, whereas lower modulation frequencies provide wide stable amplitude ranges. These insights enhance the design and safe operation of spatiotemporally modulated systems, potentially broadening their applications.</etd_ms:description>
        <etd_ms:publisher>Concordia University</etd_ms:publisher>
        <etd_ms:contributor role="advisor">Yousefzadeh, Behrooz</etd_ms:contributor>
        <etd_ms:date>2025-02-10</etd_ms:date>
        <etd_ms:type>Electronic Thesis or Dissertation</etd_ms:type>
        <etd_ms:identifier>TC-QMG-995241</etd_ms:identifier>
        <etd_ms:format>text</etd_ms:format>
        <etd_ms:identifier>https://spectrum.library.concordia.ca/id/eprint/995241/1/Wu_PhD_S2025.pdf</etd_ms:identifier>
        <etd_ms:language>en</etd_ms:language><etd_ms:degree>
        <etd_ms:name>Ph. D.</etd_ms:name>
        <etd_ms:level>phd</etd_ms:level>
        <etd_ms:discipline>Mechanical Engineering</etd_ms:discipline>
        <etd_ms:grantor>Concordia University</etd_ms:grantor></etd_ms:degree></etd_ms:thesis><etd_ms:thesis xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/ http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/etdms.xsd" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:etd_ms="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/">
        <etd_ms:title>AI-Enabled Uncrewed Aircraft System Traffic Management Methods: Hybrid Intelligence for Autonomous Navigation and Swarm Control</etd_ms:title>
        <etd_ms:creator>Xia, Bingze</etd_ms:creator>
        <etd_ms:subject/>
        <etd_ms:description>The rising global urban population has led to increased vehicles on the road and the demand for faster and more efficient transportation. As a result, the need for low-altitude spaces to support safe Unmanned Aerial Vehicles (UAV) operations has become increasingly urgent. To address this need, countries are constructing systems and implementing relevant regulations and techniques to ensure the safety of people and properties on the ground and in the air while enabling aerial vehicles to navigate and complete tasks autonomously amidst uncertainties. 
In recent years, the rapid advancement in Artificial Intelligence (AI) and a corresponding exponential increase in computing power have unlocked new possibilities. This synergy enables UAVs equipped with AI abilities to improve over time and perform complex tasks more adeptly than traditional models. This innovative direction not only expands the range of tasks that UAVs can undertake but also enhances their safety, opening up a new dimension in various sectors of human activity by leveraging the evolving capabilities of intelligent systems.
This research advances the field of safe and intelligent UAV development through a systematic, four-stage process. In the initial stage, the exploitation and improvement of advanced sensors facilitated the integration of their outputs with control systems, leading to the creation of an emergency landing system that enhances reliability. The second stage involved the design of several UAV autonomous navigation and obstacle avoidance algorithms based on diverse Reinforcement Learning (RL) algorithms. This phase also explored the performance of multiple UAV units operating in adversarial and cooperative modes, laying the groundwork for subsequent studies.
Building on the aforementioned algorithms, the third stage saw the establishment of a hybrid intelligent SAC-FIS controller. This system combines an enhanced Soft Actor-Critic (SAC) method with a Fuzzy Inference System (FIS), integrating universal expert experience to streamline the learning process. It ensures real-time path planning in three-dimensional spaces, enabling UAVs to dodge obstacles and intercept multiple dynamic targets. It addresses two significant challenges in RL: dynamic-environment problems and multi-target dilemmas.
In the final stage, a multi-layered control framework was constructed to integrate all previously developed algorithms and functionalities. This structure enables decentralized swarm control among a custom number of UAVs for dynamic target interception and includes a distributed communication strategy for effective and dynamic target allocation. The system enhances robustness and maintains low risk by activating a failsafe mode for an emergency landing whenever an individual unit in the swarm fails, allowing other units to continue and complete the mission.
The effectiveness and superiority of all proposed algorithms and the control framework have been validated by simulations and experiments. Comparisons with previously published research work highlight the enhanced efficiency and higher success rate of these approaches.</etd_ms:description>
        <etd_ms:publisher>Concordia University</etd_ms:publisher>
        <etd_ms:contributor role="advisor">Xie, Wenfang</etd_ms:contributor>
        <etd_ms:contributor role="advisor">Mantegh, Iraj</etd_ms:contributor>
        <etd_ms:date>2025-01-08</etd_ms:date>
        <etd_ms:type>Electronic Thesis or Dissertation</etd_ms:type>
        <etd_ms:identifier>TC-QMG-995146</etd_ms:identifier>
        <etd_ms:format>text</etd_ms:format>
        <etd_ms:identifier>https://spectrum.library.concordia.ca/id/eprint/995146/1/Xia_PhD_S2025.pdf</etd_ms:identifier>
        <etd_ms:language>en</etd_ms:language><etd_ms:degree>
        <etd_ms:name>Ph. D.</etd_ms:name>
        <etd_ms:level>phd</etd_ms:level>
        <etd_ms:discipline>Mechanical Engineering</etd_ms:discipline>
        <etd_ms:grantor>Concordia University</etd_ms:grantor></etd_ms:degree></etd_ms:thesis><etd_ms:thesis xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/ http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/etdms.xsd" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:etd_ms="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/">
        <etd_ms:title>Enhancing CityGML with the Built Environment End-users’ Inputs</etd_ms:title>
        <etd_ms:creator>Zarei, Farzaneh</etd_ms:creator>
        <etd_ms:subject/>
        <etd_ms:description>Enhancing CityGML with the Built Environment End-users’ Inputs  

Farzaneh Zarei, Ph.D.
Concordia University, 2025

Digitalization of infrastructure (also known as smart infrastructure or ‘smart city’) is based upon capturing and analyzing urban data and providing decision-makers with real-time analytics and insights. However, since some features of the built environment, such as citizens’ comfort, cannot be solely measured by physical sensors, there is a need for alternative tools and methods to evaluate such aspects and record the results. This exposes a key gap in current digital infrastructure models: the lack of integration between physical infrastructure data and the subjective experiences of service users.
To address this gap, this dissertation explores the following research questions:
1.	How can end-user perspectives be systematically integrated into 3D city models to better represent the performance of urban infrastructure?
2.	What kind of data schema and semantic structure are required to link social, technical, and spatial data in a standardized, extensible manner?
3.	Can such integration support practical, socially-aware decision-making in urban planning?
With these questions in mind, the dissertation proposes a new Application Domain Extension (ADE) —the Social ADE — that enables the integration of urban data streams from both internal (e.g., decision-makers) and external (e.g., infrastructure users) stakeholders into 3D city models. The Social ADE is designed to be universal and applicable across various domains of the built environment. However, this dissertation focuses on two transportation-related case studies to validate the approach, primarily due to the availability of relevant, high-quality data.
The first case study examines acoustic comfort at bus stops by integrating static (geometrical and spatial), dynamic (noise levels via mobile phones), and subjective (survey-based comfort ratings) data. The second case study presents a GIS-based method for prioritizing pothole repairs by combining technical road condition data with citizen-reported concerns to uncover latent patterns in past decision-making.
The results demonstrate that the Social ADE enables meaningful linkage between the built environment and user experiences, supporting the generation of socially-informed, human-centered insights. This research contributes a novel data integration framework that enhances the capacity of city digital twins to support inclusive and adaptive urban infrastructure planning, especially in the transportation sector.</etd_ms:description>
        <etd_ms:publisher>Concordia University</etd_ms:publisher>
        <etd_ms:contributor role="advisor">Nik-Bakht, Mazdak</etd_ms:contributor>
        <etd_ms:date>2025-01-30</etd_ms:date>
        <etd_ms:type>Electronic Thesis or Dissertation</etd_ms:type>
        <etd_ms:identifier>TC-QMG-995497</etd_ms:identifier>
        <etd_ms:format>text</etd_ms:format>
        <etd_ms:identifier>https://spectrum.library.concordia.ca/id/eprint/995497/1/Zarei_PhD_F2024.pdf</etd_ms:identifier>
        <etd_ms:language>en</etd_ms:language><etd_ms:degree>
        <etd_ms:name>Ph. D.</etd_ms:name>
        <etd_ms:level>phd</etd_ms:level>
        <etd_ms:discipline>Civil Engineering</etd_ms:discipline>
        <etd_ms:grantor>Concordia University</etd_ms:grantor></etd_ms:degree></etd_ms:thesis><etd_ms:thesis xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/ http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/etdms.xsd" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:etd_ms="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/">
        <etd_ms:title>Assessment of Urban Microclimate and Its Impacts on Building, Community, and Urban Energy Performance</etd_ms:title>
        <etd_ms:creator>Zhan, Dongxue</etd_ms:creator>
        <etd_ms:subject/>
        <etd_ms:description>With global efforts aimed at reaching carbon neutrality by 2050, there is an increased focus on improving the energy efficiency of buildings. The interactions between constructions and their local microclimate significantly influence the built environment and building energy performance. This thesis examines the urban microclimate and its impact on building energy consumption from the individual building level to entire urban areas. 
Building energy models (BEMs) are essential for understanding building energy consumption, forecasting building energy, and evaluating energy-saving measures. Meanwhile Urban Building Energy Model (UBEM) is an analytical tool for modeling buildings on city levels and evaluating scenarios for an energy-efficient built environment. However, building planners commonly overestimate cooling loads by relying on Typical Meteorological Year (TMY) data in BEM/UBEM simulations, neglecting local microclimate variations and the neighborhood effects of surrounding buildings. This research developed an integrated platform by coupling BEM/UBEM with an urban microclimate model, allowing local aerodynamic data to be exchanged between the two models at each time step. 
Since these BEM/UBEM models usually come with a deal of computation cost and prior knowledge to work with. In recent years, Machine Learning (ML) techniques in specific terms have been proposed for predicting building energy consumption. A synthetic dataset from physics-based simulations can serve as a training and testing data source for the ML model during the design phase. Weather clustering techniques are implemented to enhance computational efficiency and feasibility avoiding the high computational costs of day-by-day simulations. By employing weather clustering to select representative days, the approach reduces database size for training ML-based building prediction models.
The study begins with a comprehensive review of the latest methods for incorporating urban microclimate data into urban building energy models, addressing both methodological approaches and practical issues. Subsequently, the research evaluates the effects of urban microclimate on building energy performance, considering both individual buildings and urban-scale contexts. To address the computational cost associated with BEM/UBEM, an ML-based hourly building energy prediction model was developed, leveraging weather clustering techniques. The conclusion summarizes the key contributions of this thesis and offers recommendations for future research directions.</etd_ms:description>
        <etd_ms:publisher>Concordia University</etd_ms:publisher>
        <etd_ms:contributor role="advisor">Wang, Liangzhu</etd_ms:contributor>
        <etd_ms:contributor role="advisor">Hassan, Ibrahim</etd_ms:contributor>
        <etd_ms:date>2025-03-31</etd_ms:date>
        <etd_ms:type>Electronic Thesis or Dissertation</etd_ms:type>
        <etd_ms:identifier>TC-QMG-995339</etd_ms:identifier>
        <etd_ms:format>text</etd_ms:format>
        <etd_ms:identifier>https://spectrum.library.concordia.ca/id/eprint/995339/1/Zhan_PhD_S2025.pdf</etd_ms:identifier>
        <etd_ms:language>en</etd_ms:language><etd_ms:degree>
        <etd_ms:name>Ph. D.</etd_ms:name>
        <etd_ms:level>phd</etd_ms:level>
        <etd_ms:discipline>Building Engineering</etd_ms:discipline>
        <etd_ms:grantor>Concordia University</etd_ms:grantor></etd_ms:degree></etd_ms:thesis><etd_ms:thesis xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/ http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/etdms.xsd" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:etd_ms="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/">
        <etd_ms:title>Informative Machine Learning Model Explanation Techniques</etd_ms:title>
        <etd_ms:creator>Zhao, Ningsheng</etd_ms:creator>
        <etd_ms:subject/>
        <etd_ms:description>Explainable AI (XAI) is an emerging field focused on providing human-interpretable insights into complex and often black-box machine learning (ML) models. Shapley value attribution (SVA) is an increasingly popular XAI method that quantifies the contribution of each feature to a model’s behavior, which can be either an individual prediction (local SVAs) or a performance metric (global SVAs). However, recent research has highlighted several limitations in existing SVA methods, leading to biased or incorrect explanations that fail to capture the true relationships between features and model behaviors. What's worse, these explanations are vulnerable to adversarial manipulation. 

Additionally, global SVAs, while widely used in applied studies to gain insights into underlying information systems, face challenges when applied to ML models trained on imbalanced datasets, such as those used in fraud detection or disease prediction. In these scenarios, global SVAs can yield misleading or unstable explanations. 

This thesis aims to address these challenges and improve the reliability and informativeness of SVA explanations. It makes three key contributions: 1) Proposing a novel error analysis framework that comprehensively examines the underlying sources of bias in existing SVA methods; 2) Introducing a series of refinement methods that significantly enhance the informativeness of SVA explanations, as well as their robustness against adversarial attacks; 3) Developing a standardization method for evaluating global model behaviors on imbalanced datasets, advancing the development of an explainable model monitoring system. Our experiments demonstrate that these methods substantially improve the ability of SVAs to uncover informative patterns in model behaviors, making them valuable tools for knowledge discovery, model debugging, and performance monitoring.</etd_ms:description>
        <etd_ms:publisher>Concordia University</etd_ms:publisher>
        <etd_ms:contributor role="advisor">Yu, Jia Yuan</etd_ms:contributor>
        <etd_ms:contributor role="advisor">Zeng, Yong</etd_ms:contributor>
        <etd_ms:date>2025-01-21</etd_ms:date>
        <etd_ms:type>Electronic Thesis or Dissertation</etd_ms:type>
        <etd_ms:identifier>TC-QMG-995021</etd_ms:identifier>
        <etd_ms:format>text</etd_ms:format>
        <etd_ms:identifier>https://spectrum.library.concordia.ca/id/eprint/995021/1/Zhao_PhD_S2025.pdf</etd_ms:identifier>
        <etd_ms:language>en</etd_ms:language><etd_ms:degree>
        <etd_ms:name>Ph. D.</etd_ms:name>
        <etd_ms:level>phd</etd_ms:level>
        <etd_ms:discipline>Information and Systems Engineering</etd_ms:discipline>
        <etd_ms:grantor>Concordia University</etd_ms:grantor></etd_ms:degree></etd_ms:thesis><etd_ms:thesis xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/ http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/etdms.xsd" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:etd_ms="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/">
        <etd_ms:title>Imaging a Sense of Place and Community:
Curating Socially Engaged Art Interventions through Art-Based Action Research (ABAR)</etd_ms:title>
        <etd_ms:creator>zavarce, elsy</etd_ms:creator>
        <etd_ms:subject>Socially Engaged Art (SEA), Curatorial Practice, Sense of place, community building, Griffintown.</etd_ms:subject>
        <etd_ms:description>This dissertation investigates how innovative Socially Engaged Art (SEA) practices can cultivate a sense of community and place within rapidly transforming urban environments, focusing on Griffintown, Montreal—a historically post-industrial neighbourhood undergoing significant redevelopment. Employing Art-Based Action Research (ABAR) as its methodological framework, the study examines how art interventions can inspire social change and fortify community bonds. Three SEA interventions—a photography workshop, a collective mapping exercise, and a virtual open call—engaged diverse participants, fostering reinterpretations of Griffintown's spaces and cultivating connections among its evolving communities. Through iterative refinement and formative evaluations, the research deepened insights into the potential of SEA to foster meaningful community engagement. By fostering creativity, critical thinking, and dialogue, the interventions built a sense of place and community and contributed to the broader discourse on art's role in society. Findings highlight SEA's capacity to nurture a sense of belonging and collective identity, particularly in areas experiencing rapid urban transformation. The study emphasizes the role of socially engaged artists as curators and educators who facilitate dialogue, social integration, and cultural resilience. This dissertation advocates for curatorial practices that prioritize inclusivity, participation, and the empowerment of marginalized communities, proposing a model for curating SEA that bridges artistic, educational, and community-building endeavours. By addressing the intersections of art education, urban pedagogy, community engagement, and cultural policy, this work offers new frameworks for developing SEA interventions that promote cultural democracy and social change. This research's theoretical and practical contributions provide valuable insights for artists, educators, institutions, and policymakers, paving the way for inclusive, sustainable, and participatory pluralism in urban contexts.</etd_ms:description>
        <etd_ms:publisher>Concordia University</etd_ms:publisher>
        <etd_ms:contributor role="advisor">Blair, Lorrie</etd_ms:contributor>
        <etd_ms:date>2025-01-20</etd_ms:date>
        <etd_ms:type>Electronic Thesis or Dissertation</etd_ms:type>
        <etd_ms:identifier>TC-QMG-995353</etd_ms:identifier>
        <etd_ms:format>text</etd_ms:format>
        <etd_ms:identifier>https://spectrum.library.concordia.ca/id/eprint/995353/2/Zavarce_PhD_S2025.pdf</etd_ms:identifier>
        <etd_ms:language>en</etd_ms:language><etd_ms:degree>
        <etd_ms:name>Ph. D.</etd_ms:name>
        <etd_ms:level>phd</etd_ms:level>
        <etd_ms:discipline>Art Education</etd_ms:discipline>
        <etd_ms:grantor>Concordia University</etd_ms:grantor></etd_ms:degree></etd_ms:thesis><etd_ms:thesis xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/ http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/etdms.xsd" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:etd_ms="http://www.ndltd.org/standards/metadata/etdms/1.0/">
        <etd_ms:title>Imprints of vector-like fermions on electroweak vacuum
stability in extended Higgs frameworks</etd_ms:title>
        <etd_ms:creator>Çıngılolu, Kıvanç Yiğit</etd_ms:creator>
        <etd_ms:subject/>
        <etd_ms:description>The issue of electroweak vacuum stability in the Standard Model remains a significant theoretical challenge. This thesis investigates the role of vector-like fermions in stabilizing the electroweak vacuum. We focus on three scenarios: the Higgs-Scalar Model with Vector-Like Quarks, Two-Higgs Doublet Model with Vector-Like Quarks, and Vector-Like Leptons in the Standard Model, exploring how the introduction of these additional fermions can modify the stability of the vacuum. We examine all gauge-anomaly-free vector-like representations under the SM gauge symmetry, and we analyze each of these models, taking into account all experimental constraints and electroweak precision observables, and considering both direct and indirect constraints from collider and cosmological data. The
work shows that, under certain conditions for the vector-like fermion masses and mixing parameters, the electroweak vacuum can be stabilized in all models studied, providing a viable mechanism for addressing the vacuum stability problem in the Standard Model.</etd_ms:description>
        <etd_ms:publisher>Concordia University</etd_ms:publisher>
        <etd_ms:contributor role="advisor">Frank, Mariana</etd_ms:contributor>
        <etd_ms:date>2025-01-15</etd_ms:date>
        <etd_ms:type>Electronic Thesis or Dissertation</etd_ms:type>
        <etd_ms:identifier>TC-QMG-995205</etd_ms:identifier>
        <etd_ms:format>text</etd_ms:format>
        <etd_ms:identifier>https://spectrum.library.concordia.ca/id/eprint/995205/1/Cingiloglu_PhD_S2025.pdf</etd_ms:identifier>
        <etd_ms:language>en</etd_ms:language><etd_ms:degree>
        <etd_ms:name>Ph. D.</etd_ms:name>
        <etd_ms:level>phd</etd_ms:level>
        <etd_ms:discipline>Physics</etd_ms:discipline>
        <etd_ms:grantor>Concordia University</etd_ms:grantor></etd_ms:degree></etd_ms:thesis></collection>